<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<atom:link href="http://pomax.github.io/gh-weblog-2/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<title>Pomax.github.io</title>
<description>My blog on github</description>
<link>http://pomax.github.io</link>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 03:17:56 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 03:17:56 GMT</pubDate>
<ttl>1440</ttl>
<item>
<title> React with LaTeX, without needing client-side Mathjax</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;It's no secret that I like working with &lt;a href="https://facebook.github.io/react"&gt;React&lt;/a&gt;, and that I like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LaTeX"&gt;LaTeX&lt;/a&gt; for my maths, and that I like &lt;a href="https://mathjax.org"&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt; for my LaTeX on the web. What I don't like, though, is having to wait 20 seconds for a long article with lots of maths to load client-side, constantly changing the page dimensions as it does so. Especially if you're loading it mid-page and then MathJax kicks in and all the content keeps being pushed down. And again. And again, etc. etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's annoying for the user, and as the guy who runs a &lt;a href="http://pomax.github.io/bezierinfo"&gt;big article on Bézier curves&lt;/a&gt;, with lots of maths, it's annoying to know I'm responsible for a bad experience. So, I'm rewriting that article so that it's easier to maintain, and loads a million times faster. One of the things that involves is taking MathJax out of the client-side experience, which means during LaTeX conversion server-side. Or really, "offline", because it should be a "generate once, then cache and use" instead of "having the server generate it all the time".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="react-and-webpack-and-babel-"&gt;React and Webpack (and Babel)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, a React codebase needs bundling, and generally also some &lt;a href="https://facebook.github.io/react/docs/jsx-in-depth.html"&gt;JSX&lt;/a&gt; transforming and &lt;a href="https://babeljs.io/docs/learn-es2015"&gt;ES2015+&lt;/a&gt; conversion, so the basis for my rewrite was a fairly simple dir layout with a fairly simple &lt;a href="https://webpack.github.io"&gt;Webpack&lt;/a&gt; config:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;./
 |-&amp;lt;components&amp;gt;
 |-&amp;lt;images&amp;gt;
 |-&amp;lt;lib&amp;gt; 
 |-&amp;lt;stylesheets&amp;gt;
 | package.json
 | webpack.config.js
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the Webpack config doing the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var webpack = require('webpack');

// Hot Reload server when we're in dev mode, otherwise build it the normal way.
var entry = ['./components/App.jsx'];
if(!process.argv.indexOf("--prod")) { entry.push('webpack/hot/dev-server'); }

module.exports = {
  entry:  entry,
  output: {
    path: __dirname,
    filename: 'article.js'
  },
  module: {
    loaders: [
      { test: /\.(png|gif)$/, loader: "file?name=images/packed/[hash].[ext]" },
      { test: /\.less$/, loader: "style!css!less" },
      { test: /.jsx?$/, include: /components/, loaders: ['babel-loader']
      }
    ]
  },
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty standard setup, with webpack's &lt;a href="https://webpack.github.io/docs/hot-module-replacement-with-webpack.html"&gt;"hot reloading" server&lt;/a&gt; for dev work, and no server for production builds. Running Webpack for production will yield a file &lt;code&gt;article.js&lt;/code&gt; in the root, based on starting at the &lt;code&gt;component/App.jsx&lt;/code&gt; file, and then just bundling in every little requirement that has until we run out of things that need to be bundled in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see I'm using &lt;a href="http://babeljs.io"&gt;Babel&lt;/a&gt; for interpreting any js/jsx files (it takes care of JSX transforming and ES2015 syntax), as well as &lt;a href="http://lesscss.org"&gt;less&lt;/a&gt; for my CSS. There's also a dumb &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/file-loader"&gt;"file-loader"&lt;/a&gt; which simply copies images into their own dir. Not always necessary, but useful when running the webpack dev server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I trigger either dev or prod runs is via &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/k88hudson/advanced-frontend-automation-with-npm-scripts"&gt;npm scripts&lt;/a&gt;, with the &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; using the following script block:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  ...
  "scripts": {
    "build": "webpack --prod",
    "start": "webpack-dev-server --progress --colors --hot --inline",
  },
  ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two commands, a short &lt;code&gt;$&amp;gt; npm start&lt;/code&gt; for dev work, since that gets run all the time, and a special &lt;code&gt;$&amp;gt; npm run build&lt;/code&gt; for when the production bundle needs to be built. So far so good!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="adding-latex-to-react-components"&gt;Adding LaTeX to React components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I hate when doing rewrites is "changing everything" to suit the technology. The article as it exists relies on LaTeX that takes the following form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;\[
  f(x) = \sum^n_{k=0} \frac{n(n-k)}{k! + x} 
\]&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;That's a pretty standard format if you use MathJax, or &lt;a href="https://github.com/Khan/KaTeX"&gt;KaTeX&lt;/a&gt;, and since I use a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of LaTeX, that format had to stay. And that's a bit of a problem, because LaTeX uses a lot of curly brackets. And React's JSX syntax treats curly brackets as templating delimiters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something like this, for instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;\[
  \frac{percentage}{100}
\]&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;will cause the JSX transform step to go "uh, I don't know a variable &lt;code&gt;percentage&lt;/code&gt;, I can't convert this for you". Even though we don't want it converted. Too bad for us! However, there is a way out, and it's called a Webpack loader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="webpack-and-mathjax-node"&gt;Webpack and mathjax-node&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed the part where I mentioned Webpack uses babel for JSX and ES2015 transforms. That means it rewrites the source code several times before handing it off for bundling, and so if we can convert those LaTeX blocks before anything else tries to interpret it, things should work pretty well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let us write a latex-loader for Webpack. In fact, I've already done the work there, so, let's look at that. First off, Webpack &lt;strong&gt;is weird&lt;/strong&gt; when it comes to loader order, and uses a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stack_%28abstract_data_type%29"&gt;LIFO&lt;/a&gt; ordering. The last loader gets to run first. So:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;loaders: [
  ...
  {
    test: /.jsx?$/,
    include: /components/,
    loaders: [
      'babel-loader',
      __dirname + '/lib/latex-loader'
    ]
  }
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;With a corresponding &lt;code&gt;latex-loader.js&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;code&gt;./lib&lt;/code&gt; dir:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var op = "\\[";
var ed = "\\]";

/**
 * Is there going to be anything to convert here?
 */
function hasLaTeX(input) {
  return input.indexOf(op) !== -1 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; input.indexOf(ed) !== -1;
}

/**
 * We look for MathJax/KaTeX style data, and make sure
 * it is escaped properly so that JSX conversion will
 * still work.
 */
function escapeBlockLaTeX(source) {
  // MAGIC HAPPENS HERE!
  return doTheMagic(source);
}

module.exports = function(source) {
  this.cacheable();
  if (!hasLaTeX(source)) return source;
  return escapeBlockLaTeX(source);
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;That's the main gist of it, anyway. The loader's basically a single synchronous function that gets passed entire files as source string, and then expects a possible different string as replacement output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the approach is obvious: accept the source only if it has LaTeX that needs transforming (otherwise just hand the original source back as a thing we don't need to change), and then if we're still running, find all the LaTeX blocks, transform them to "something safe", and then return that modified source. Ideally, transform them using MathJax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, MathJax has a server-side library available called &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/mathjax-node"&gt;mathjax-node&lt;/a&gt;, which can be used to generate browser-agnostic SVG or MathML source, so that's perfect! It means we can do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var mathjax = require("mathjax-node");

function escapeBlockLaTeX(source) {
  var from = 0, curr, term, newsource = "", latex;
  for(curr = source.indexOf(op, from);
      curr !== -1;
      from = term + ed.length, curr = source.indexOf(op, from))
  {
    // split out a block of LaTeX:
    newsource += source.substring(from, curr);
    term = source.indexOf(ed, from);
    if(term === -1) {
      // We only have ourselves to blame if we get here
      throw new Error("improperly closed LaTeX encountered!");
    }
    latex = source.substring(curr, term + ed.length);

    // convert this LaTeX code to SVG, which React can deal with just fine:
    var mathjaxed = mathjax.typeset(latex);

    // slot the SVG code in place of the LaTeX code
    newsource += mathjaxed;
  }
  return newsource + source.substring(from);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Except... we can't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="webpack-mathjax-and-the-problem-of-sync-vs-async"&gt;Webpack, MathJax, and the problem of sync vs. async&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, Webpack is a fully synchronous technology. A loader gets a file, transforms it, then passes it back to webpack, which hands it to the next loader, which transforms it, and so on. This is a fully synchronous process, and loaders simply get data, and "immediately" (give or take the time needed to modify that data) give something back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MathJax can't do that. It relies on quite a few asynchronous things (like font loads), and so where webpack has a function API much like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;module.exports = function webpackloader(input) {
  return formOutput(input);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;MathJax has a function API like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mathjax.typeset(input, function(result) {
  if(!result.errors) {
    doSomethingWith(result.svg);
  }
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;That doesn't look too strange, &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/748175/asynchronous-vs-synchronous-execution-what-does-it-really-mean"&gt;but the timing is crucially different&lt;/a&gt;: when the Webpack loader runs, its function is entered, data is transformed, and it exits again. However, when the MathJax typesetter runs, the function call happens and then &lt;em&gt;immediately exits again&lt;/em&gt;, and at some point in the future the result handling function will run, and there is no way to "wait" for it to finish, because that's not a thing JavaScript can do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If only there was a way that we could turn the asynchronouse conversion process that MathJax requires, into a synchronous data transform as is required by Webpack...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="execsync-ing-our-way-to-success"&gt;execSync'ing our way to success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in that wish we find the answer: make the conversion a command line utility, and then &lt;code&gt;exec&lt;/code&gt; that utility synchronously, using &lt;a href="https://nodejs.org"&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt;'s built in &lt;a href="https://nodejs.org/api/child_process.html#child_process_child_process_execsync_command_options"&gt;execSync&lt;/a&gt;, because the following will work brilliantly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var execSync = require("child_process").execSync;

function escapeBlockLaTeX(source) {
  ...
  for(...) {
    // split out a block of LaTeX:
    latex = ...

    // convert all this!
    var mathjaxed = execSync("node tex2svg.js --latex " + latex);

    // slot the rewritten code back in
    newsource += mathjaxed;
  }
  ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We write a simple &lt;code&gt;tex2svg.js&lt;/code&gt; file that requires &lt;code&gt;mathjax-node&lt;/code&gt;, passes it the config options for conversion to SVG, read in the LaTeX as command line argument, and then spits out the conversion result on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_streams"&gt;standard out&lt;/a&gt;, so that &lt;code&gt;execSync&lt;/code&gt; treats it as its function return value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here's where things get tricky. Writing a command line utility that does the MathJax conversion requires a little work, because the command line is tricky, and LaTeX contains all kinds of characters that can do things in shell land. Slashes and ampersands abound, and those are kind of active symbols,  so we need to be a little smarter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// convert all this... smarter!
var base64 = new Buffer(latex).toString("base64");
var mathjaxed = execSync("node tex2svg.js --base54 " + base64);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And then we just need to make sure that the mathjax script unpacks the passed data from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Base64"&gt;base 64 format&lt;/a&gt; to plain string format before converting, and we're good!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not quite: this is not exactly a cheap thing to do. Firing up an instance of node and loading &lt;code&gt;mathjax-node&lt;/code&gt; takes time. Not enough to notice if you only do it once, but if you need to run this lots of times, a second each time adds up to having to wait minutes for this building to happen. Every time you want to run the dev server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That is unacceptable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let's add in some caching: instead of having the MathJax script do the conversion for us, and then spit out the SVG code, we make it do the conversion but then write the SVG code to file, in the images dir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And because we don't want the build process to do more work than necessary, we make the filenames predictable, based on the LaTeX that needs to be converted: we compute the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SHA-1"&gt;sha1 digest&lt;/a&gt; of the LaTeX that needs converting, and only if we don't see a file called &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;hash&amp;gt;.svg&lt;/code&gt; in the images dir do we do our conversion:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var sha1 = require("sha1");

function escapeBlockLaTeX(source) {
  ...
  for(...) {
    latex = ...;

    // Get the digest for the latex - any subsequent checks for the same block
    // of LaTeX will yield the exact same digest, which is handy!
    var hash = sha1.hash(latex);

    // Whether the SVG for this LaTeX already exists or not, we already know
    // the filename it's going to have, so we can prebuild the JSX we need:  
    var imgHTML = '&amp;lt;img src="' + hash + '.svg" className="LaTeX SVG"/&amp;gt;';

    // Then: do we need to generate this image first? If so, execSync,
    // otherwise we do absolutely nothing because we're already done!  
    if (!imageExists(hash)) {
      var base64 = new Buffer(latex).toString("base64");
      execSync("node tex2svg.js --hash " + hash +" --base54 " + base64);
    }

    newsource += imgHTML;
  }
  return newsource;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And that, as they say, is that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="boom-"&gt;Boom.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this latex-loader in conjunction with a file writing conversion utility script, we now have a &lt;em&gt;synchronous&lt;/em&gt; MathJax conversion going on, despite MathJax itself being an inherently asynchronous processor, and we completely bypass any strangeness that might normally pop up if you tried to mix LaTeX code and JSX syntax, with the benefit of files that can be cached, so that the browser doesn't need to redownload them everytime the article gets loaded in a browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responsiveness increase: x1 million. Goal reached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of every individual user needing to wait for MathJax to do typesetting, the only person waiting for MathJax now is me, and only for "new" LaTeX blocks during the build step. &lt;em&gt;As it should be&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can add sections one at a time, and every time I run the build step, only genuinely new LaTeX will need to get converted. LaTeX that got processed during a previous run already wrote files to disk, so the latex-loader just bypasses the conversion process entirely in for those LaTeX blocks, and so the build really only does exactly as much work as it needs to do to get the data transformed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I am chuffed to bits about this, and if you have any questions about the process, feel free to reach out to me &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/TheRealPomax"&gt;on twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://github.com/Pomax/BezierInfo-2/issues"&gt;on github&lt;/a&gt;, and I'll be happy to talk about it more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>React</category>
<category>LaTeX</category>
<category>MathJax</category>
<category>Webpack</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1451617530567</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1451617530567</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 03:05:30 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> Developing Open Source Software</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I want to take a little bit of time to explain how I work on Open Source, both privately and as part of my job as a Software Engineer at the Mozilla Foundation. Not because it's wildly different from how everyone else does it, but because it's probably the same as how the vast majority works on Open Source, which means very few people bother to explain the processes involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two different kinds of "working on open source", depending on whether the code is a collaboration or just a simple one-person project, so let's look at both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-i-m-making-a-thing-"&gt;&lt;em&gt;"I'm making a thing!"&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're making a thing, the basic rule is "anything goes": you're the only one you're inconveniencing by taking shortcuts, and often that's fine. However, if you're starting a project that you think might at some point gain contributors (say, you're making a thing that you hope becomes popular), there are a few things you can do to make sure that when your project does go from "one dev" to "a team", the transition is smooth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="file-issues-before-fixing-them"&gt;File issues before fixing them&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only is it a handy If you file the issues you know about as a kind of to-do list to walk through, but you might be surprised to find someone actually fixing an issue you filed before you get to it, once your project gets even a little exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="work-in-branches-"&gt;Work in branches.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be an initial "I just need to get this code written" period where you're pushing to master: awesome, go for it. However, once you reach what might turn into a 1.0 with a bit more code, start getting in the habit of treating your master branch as off limits, and working in branches that you merge into master instead. This makes it easier for contributors to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="document-document-document-"&gt;Document, document, document.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're not actually working on your code alone: you're collaborating with your future self, and future self has no idea what you're thinking right now while you're writing your code: document your choices, explain complex bits of code and whatever you do, explain hacks and bodges! Clever as they might be today, 2 months from now they might be so clever you actually need to spend your own time on them to figure out why they even work the way they do. Help future-you out: write documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that doesn't need to be wikis or long readmes, it can just be code comments: as long as knowledge you need to understand changes you're making right now isn't lost, you're being awesome. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-we-re-making-a-thing-"&gt;&lt;em&gt;We're making a thing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you're fairly free to do what you want to do on your own, for collaborative projects, there is really only one way to work in a way that's not going to break down. For anything that needs to be done, follow the three F's:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;File it&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fix it&lt;/strong&gt;, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow up&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="1-file-it-"&gt;1) File it!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're going to work on something, make sure it's a known issue. Code changes without an issue that explain why the changes were necessary in the first place are mystery changes, and mysteries in a collaborative effort are bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, that doesn't mean the changes aren't necessary, so: always, &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; make sure there's a ticket, or issue, or bug report, associated with the changes you're making, so that your code changes can say "this fixes/addresses ticket/issue/bug so-and-so". Sometimes those tickets/issues/bug reports already exist and you can simply refer to them, but sometimes they don't: &lt;strong&gt;file it before submitting your code changes&lt;/strong&gt;, so that you can refer to that newly filed ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's okay to already have the code in place that addresses an issue you haven't filed yet, just make sure that by the time you submit your changes, there is one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collaboration relies on communication. If people change the code without tying it to the list of "these are issues we need to address", then there is no way to track changes in the codebase. Generating a changelog based on closed issues is often quite easy, but if there are no issues that got closed/resolved due to changes getting accepted into the code base, then you're asking people to work on code that potentially no one can explain (because the person who contributed it may have left already. If you can even track who submitted the change at all).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;strong&gt;file individual issues&lt;/strong&gt;. The best code bases are ones where each thing that needs to be done is filed separately, and fixed separately, because it's much easier to work on as a team (small tasks make for rapid progress), and it makes it easy to track complex tasks: if you need to implement a user profile system, and that requires a login system, a user database, and user facing UI, then if someone files "implement a user profile system", the very first thing that should happen is chopping that issue up into several smaller issues. It might sound anal, but you're working in a team, and many hands make light work: the smaller you can chop up an issue, the easier it becomes to resolve the bigger task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="2-fix-it-"&gt;2) Fix it...&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crazy as it may sound: never start fixing things by writing code. First ask: "Has someone else already written the code and can I just plug that in?". If they have: just use that. You're still probably going to need a little bit of code to do the "plugging it in" part, but little bits of code are easy to maintain, and it means you're not responsible for maintaining lots of code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, if there is no code out there that already does what you need to do, ask yourself: "Can I write this as a standalone utility, and then plug &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; in?". Because if you can, that's worth doing. If you need to solve a problem and there's no solution out there, you're probably solving a problem that other people are also having: it's worth making that solution available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there will be plenty of issues that can only be addressed by writing real, project-relevant, code, and for those occasions there are three things to keep in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;commit early&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;commit often&lt;/strong&gt;, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;communicate with your team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="commit-early"&gt;Commit early&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're working on code changes, push up your changes as soon as you have "something" going. &lt;strong&gt;Especially if it's not done yet&lt;/strong&gt;. Don't wait until "it's done", because you have no idea when that will be: form a commit and push it up once you have the basic stubs in place, for instance, before you start working out the code in full.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lets other people that work with you see what you're working on, and lets them catch things early that would cost a lot of time to fix later on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="commit-often"&gt;Commit often&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some code changes are one liners or a simple function renaming, but many are not: don't wait until you're done to push up your changes. Any time you write some code and test it, and it passes, that's a moment to form a commit, push it up, and then keep going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a computer dies (and if you work in a team, that will happen surprisingly often) or someone unexpectedly becomes unavailable for a few days (again, happens more often than you might think), there is no loss of work &lt;strong&gt;for the team&lt;/strong&gt;. The team as a whole can pick up where you as a person left off in these circumstances, and if you don't commit often, they'll potentially have to reinvent changes you had already written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also much easier to rebase your code if they're small incremental commits when the master code base changes. For instance, a dependency got updated, which caused some functions to use that dependency's new API calls; that is much easier to deal with if it just requires you to change the small commit that touched a file for which that was the case than if you have one massive commit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the more often you commit, the earlier possible bugs can be found; the earlier bugs are found, the less work it is to fix them, because not a lot of things will trigger them yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="communicate-with-your-team"&gt;Communicate with your team&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're working on anything even moderately sized: start talking about your code with team members early. Don't ask them to review only all the way at the end if your changes involve new code or new approaches; run it by someone so that even if you're the only one that'll end up writing code, you're &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the only one who knows what decisions were made while the code was being written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, remember to ask questions in the open. You might end up with blocking questions that need an answer before you can continue your work, and while it's tempting to try to find someone to get it answered in real-time, &lt;strong&gt;file it first&lt;/strong&gt;, so that the entire team can see it. Then you can find someone to real-time answer it and capture the answer in the filed issue, so that the entire team can be aware of the question having come up, and the answer that was agreed on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="corrolary-know-when-to-split-your-work-"&gt;Corrolary: know when to split your work.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some issues reveal problems in other parts of the project, and you might be tempted to fix those as part of your changes. I know it's tempting, but &lt;strong&gt;don't&lt;/strong&gt;, because you're not actually helping the team that way. Instead: file it, fix it, and follow up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Step away from the current code when you reach a good break point (and that could be immediately, if the thing you found is blocking you),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;File the issue as a new issue,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it's blocking you:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix it first,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schedule follow up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rebase your code on the fix, so you're unblocked&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now you can come back to the code you were already working on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll note that in step 3 the advice is to work on it immediately only if it's actually blocking you: this is important. You're working in a team, and someone else might have a free moment to work on the thing you just discovered, while you keep working on your own changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="3-run-through-the-follow-up-"&gt;3) Run through the follow-up.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You've worked on code changes, you committed early, and often, and your "patch" now consists of 12 commits and two observations about future work: it's time for follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="clean-up-your-code"&gt;Clean up your code&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your changes work using 12 commits, then your changes work, and it's time to squash those 12 commits into a single commit so it can be landed into the codebase without all the steps that got you there. Even if there is no requirement to squash your code before landing, changelog generation, revision control, and rollbacks are all much nicer if patches land as single commits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, if there are any unnecessary comments or logs/prints in your code, now's the time to get rid of those, and of course, now is also the time to make sure that any missing documentation either gets added, or gets filed as "document XYZ", to be worked on immediately after landing your changes, rather than anything else, which brings us to...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="file-anything-you-found-but-didn-t-fix-"&gt;File anything you found, but didn't fix.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you were working on your changes, you may have thought of things that might need addressing outside of the changes you made: &lt;strong&gt;file those&lt;/strong&gt;. It is important to capture those observations in a way that the entire team can see them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="talk-to-your-team"&gt;Talk to your team&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, follow up with people, too. Let the people who need to know about your changes know about your changes - ask them to review you patch, explain your work to them where needed, if there is testing involved, make sure they understand what needs to be done, and generally make sure at least two people agree these changes are good to go (including yourself). That communication doesn't need to happen in person, the issue tracker you use might facilitate this kind of follow up, but always collaborate on the landing, even if the code works. There might be last minute changes or decisions that you were not aware of that someone else might: good to discover that before the changes are merged in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="that-s-pretty-much-it"&gt;That's pretty much it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a fair amount of finer detail and variation that fits into the "file it, fix it, follow up" process, but stick to that order and you're on the path of a sustainable development cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of this is probably obvious to most people, but that just makes it all the more important to get it written down, because someone's going to be a bit bewildered and they'll need a blog post to get them on track =)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Open source</category>
<category>Development</category>
<category>Process</category>
<category>Mozilla</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1450207129290</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1450207129290</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 19:18:49 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> OpenType: let's learn how modern fonts actually work</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In a previous post &lt;a href="/1449438115186"&gt;I talked about the distinction between "TTF" and "OTF" fonts&lt;/a&gt;, and the fact that they're actually both just OpenType fonts. I explained how the difference between TTF and OTF is only which outline language is used, with everything else being the same between the two types of Opentype font, so in this post I'd like to talk about some of the bits that all OpenType fonts have. There are actually quite a lot of things, so this will not be the last post on the subject, but let's just cover as much as we can and see what that leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with something that might sound like it can't possibly be true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fonts-don-t-contain-letters-"&gt;Fonts don't contain letters.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know this sounds a bit weird for a technology that is supposed to be used to draw letters, but it's important to get this out of the way first: fonts don't know anything about "letters". Instead, they know about character codes, and glyphs. Character codes are simply numbers that the computer sees when you type, when it reads a text file, etc. and glyphs are anything in the font "that can be drawn". A font is a collection of inherently meaningless pictures, linked to character codes to give them meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-problem-with-defining-letters-"&gt;The problem with defining "letters"&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason fonts contain character codes and glyphs, rather than "letters" is that letters are a very restricted class of things we write. For instance, clearly the "letters" a through z are letters; this is true by definition. But are numbers letters? We can say that Fonts contain numbers and letters, but then what about symbols? Okay, fonts contain numbers, letters, and symbols. Clearly we're done. But what about CJK languages? Their writing systems don't use "letters": Korean has syllables, instead, Chinese has logograms, and Japanese uses both. So now things are getting very tricky. But let's make it even more fun: let's look at different kinds of the same letter. In English, the 'a' and the 'A' are both the same letter, as well as different letters. If you had to group the elements of a set "a,a,A,a,a,A,A,b,A,b,b,a,B,B,B", you would probably group them as a's in one pile, and b's in another. But if you had to group a full mixture of the alphabet in upper and lowercase, you'd probably sort them according to case. Are they the same letter or different letters? What about Arabic, in which each letter has four possible shapes depending on where in a word it's used (a letter will look different depending on whether it's on its own, or at the start of, middle of, or end of a word). What about those, are those all different letters, or the same one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in order to get around this problem, fonts don't contain letters. They contain &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glyph"&gt;glyphs&lt;/a&gt;: anything that you can draw an outline for can be made a glyph, so that in a font: yes, all those different forms of the same thing are different things, and it's up to the character mapping and substitution rules specified in the Opentype font to determine which glyph should be used when.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="character-code-sets"&gt;Character code sets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where do the character mappings come from? How many are there? Which are "the best"?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For convenience, I'm going to ignore a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of history, mostly because you can write full chapters on the history of character mappings, and we'd still not get to where I want to get in this post, so: lots of different people and organisations have coined lots of different character mappings throughout the history of computing, and of those, I want to focus on two major ones: ASCII, and Unicode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASCII"&gt;ASCII&lt;/a&gt; is probably the oldest, still widely used, standard, and it was invented to capture the symbols used in American computing, using 7 bits. Because back in the day, there weren't necessarily 8 bits to a byte, sometimes you have 7, or 6, or some other value that we now think of as weirdly "not eight". Anyway, ASCII uses 7 bits, and so there are 128 possible codes available: 0 through 127. The first 32 codes are "control" codes, not so much related to typing things as controlling the computer: escape, backspace, tabulation, line feed, data acknowledgement, things that control what the computer will do. After that are the numbers, letters, and symbols that were commonly (and a few uncommonly) used in American computing environments, and the very last code is the "delete" code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, at the same time the rest of the world was inventing tons of other encodings because America wasn't the only country in the world using computers, and as the world became more and more connected, the more we had problems around trying to read text written by someone who wasn't using the same encoding, as well as needing way more than just 128 "spots" to capture all the different things necessary for each language, let alone "all languages".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's where &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode"&gt;Unicode&lt;/a&gt; comes in: Unicode was, and remains, our best effort to fit all writing systems in this world into a single character mapping. As you can imagine, that mapping is huge: over 120,000 codes at this point in history (in June 2015, the Unicode standard v8 was released). But: the standard is public, it's stable (meaning that it's never going to fix historical mistakes like two different codes that point to the same character, but that no one noticed before accepting the code into the standard), and it takes a fairly long time to get new codes assigned specifically to make sure that standard doesn't "just grow" as we add more and more languages into it, but actually has some internal logic that computer scientists, programmers, etc. can rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing that made switching to Unicode even possible, was that the first 128 codes in Unicode are, in fact, the ASCII codes, which made it possible to switch from ASCII to Unicode with virtually no effort. ASCII data, in an 8 bit world, is automatically data that matches the Unicode mappings, "encoded using the UTF-8 scheme".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="byte-encodings"&gt;Byte encodings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a standard that contains way more numbers than fit in 8 bits, you need an extra step to turn possibly huge numbers into sequences of bits. Where ASCII is both the character code set and the encoding, Unicode needs a bit more work: it is only the character code set, and in order to write those codes as bytes on a disk, it has various "byte encoding" schemes available. All of these encode "Unicode data", but byte patterns on the disk can look radically different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two common encodings for Unicode are things you've probably heard of, even if you don't know what they are exactly: UTF-8, or UTF-16. For details on both, wikipedia is a great source of information, so I will just summarise them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-16"&gt;UTF-16&lt;/a&gt; simply "tried" to capture every code using 16 bits, and then when there were so many codes that it became obvious that 16 bits would not be enough, a special few codes were reserved for "if you see this code, it's actually not a character mapping itself, but has to be combined with the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; 16 bits to form one of the higher numbers that don't fit in 16 bits".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this description, you'd imagine that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8"&gt;UTF-8&lt;/a&gt; does something similar, and it totally does, except it's generally far more efficient than UTF-16 in how it does it; UTF-8 is a variable byte encoding, with marker bits to say how many bytes are used, and whether a byte is a "start" byte or a follow-up byte. It matches ASCII byte-for-byte by starting with the bit 0 ("there are no next bytes") and then the 7 bit ASCII value. For any value larger than 128, needing more than 1 byte, the first byte starts as 1,1,0 if there are going to be 2 bytes used, 1,1,1,0 for three, 1,1,1,1,0 for four, etc. Any subsequent byte starts with 1,0 (so if you pick a random spot in a UTF-8 stream, and you see a byte that starts as 1,0 you know you need to move forward or backward a little so you're not in the middle of a character's code representation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="from-code-sets-to-glyphs"&gt;from code sets to glyphs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So on the conceptual side, we have "things you can write", which we capture as glyphs in a font, and a character mapping that assigns each of those things a number, but then we still have a problem: fonts don't have to implement every possible character, so if we look at the character mappings that are actually &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; in a font, there might be lots of disjointed sets of supported, and not supported mappings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fonts, on the other hand, are relatively efficient in how they store glyphs: they use arrays. The first glyph is in spot 0, the second glyph is in spot 1, the third in spot 2, and so forth: they are a stored in a list without gaps, and their ordering in that list is not related to any encoding or character mapping. It's just a list of pictures with ids derived directly from their position in the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So even if we have our list of glyphs, and we know which character mapping our font will work with, and we know which parts of that mapping the font will support, we still need one more step to make sure we can look up with character code maps to which position in the font's list of glyphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-internal-glyphs"&gt;"internal" glyphs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there can also be glyphs that don't map to character codes. This sounds a bit odd, because how would you ever see them, but glyphs don't need to specify all the outline data in a giant wad of instructions: they can also contain references to other glyphs. For instance, the Japanese character 松 (pine tree) and 柿 (persimmon) have the same "drawing" on the left side. We can store that particular outline as an internal glyph, with its own glyph id, and then form those two characters by starting each off as saying "place the glyph at id ... on the left" before explicitly specifying the outlines for the rest of the glyph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, a font kind of &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; contain gaps in the list of glyphs, not by having "nothing" in the list in some spots, but by having glyphs that don't have a mapping to any character code. Things can get really tricky!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-cmap-table"&gt;The CMAP Table&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point you might think: "...but there are so many encodings and character mappings and no rules on how to order glyphs in that list, there must be millions of ways for that final mapping to look!" And you're not wrong. There really are an incredible number of "character code to font-internal glyph id" mappings that could exist, and so OpenType comes with not just one, but several different ways to set up a "character to glyph id" mapping, based on a few things like "does the font implement one, or multiple, sets of character codes", "can there be gaps in the sets or not", "are any of the sets not commonly implemented sets", etc. By answering these questions, you can find the best charcode to id mapping for what your font will support, and then based on that you can follow a small number of rules around how to order the glyphs in the list of glyphs so that everything will work efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing that makes this work in OpenType fonts is called the &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/typography/otspec/cmap.htm"&gt;&lt;code&gt;CMAP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; table, and if you're still thinking "wait, that sounds like still not enough to capture all those possibilities", you're still right, and OpenType lets you specify &lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt; CMAP subtables, which can all be different, to efficiently cover the entire range of supported characters in your font.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you might think that the pictures inside the font are the most important part of a font, in terms of how fonts &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;, the CMAP is the absolutely most important part: if the outlines are missing, but we have a CMAP, at least the CMAP can tell us there are no pictures to work with, and if any of the OpenType metadata is missing, we might be rendering the text in a really weird way, but without a CMAP we don't even know what characters a font supports, or how to even get to any of the pictures we need to render text. Without a CMAP, a font is just a useless binary file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And yes, historically there have been font formats that actually had outline data in one file, being the 'useless binary file', and a separate cmap file that you could load to give meaning to the 'useless data')&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="substitutions"&gt;Substitutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we need one more thing to deal with issues around "which glyph do we even use?" such as what we saw for Arabic: one letter, but depending on where in a word it is, it has to look different. Or closer to English: ligatures, where typing an 'f' followed by an 'i' tends to generate some shape fi that looks different, and is in fact a different glyph, from the separate letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is called "substitution", and is handled by a table called the &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/typography/otspec/gsub.htm"&gt;&lt;code&gt;GSUB&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; table. It allows various kinds of substitutions, with rules that can be different depending on the language or script the font has to style: substitution rules for English may not need to apply in Vietnamese, for instance. In order to deal with all kinds of substitutions, the GSUB table is &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/typography/otspec/chapter2.htm"&gt;split up into several sections&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scripts, which say which "language" the text is in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;features, which control when substitutions kick in (such as common ligatures, historical number forms, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lookups, which are the actual "A becomes B" rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a substitution set up, you need a lookup (to say which actual substitution has to happen), tied to a feature (which gives the typographical context for the lookup), tied to a script (which gives the linguistic context for the feature). All of these are many-to-many, so one feature could be used by multiple scripts, and one script can use multiple features (and then the same for features and lookup relations).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Substitution lookups also come in various forms, so that there are special structions for one-for-one substitutions (like turning every full stop into a Japanese sentence end marker), many-for-one (like word to icon substitution), initial, medial, and final substitutions (for languages like Arabic) and the rather complicated "contextual substitution" which lets you define patterns in the text that have to be true for the substitution to kick in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="wrapping-up"&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it's tempting to argue about TTF vs OTF, the thing that really drives a font is the CMAP. Hopefully you now understand the core concept for modern OpenType fonts a bit better, understanding how a font knows which characters it supports, and how it it maps what you type to what you see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a next post I'll cover some more typographical concepts like kerning and positioning, as well as some of the finer nuances between TrueType and Type2 outlines, which work together with the pure OpenType data about those things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you have questions, or comments, do let me know by clicking the comment link below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Fonts</category>
<category>OpenType</category>
<category>CMAP</category>
<category>GSUB</category>
<category>TTF</category>
<category>OTF</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1449777175633</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1449777175633</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 19:52:55 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> OpenType: what's the difference between TTF and OTF??</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a multiparter, because I've been trying to write this as a single long read and it's just not working. So as the first part in part of an OpenType series: ttf and otf... what's the difference?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="first-it-s-all-opentype"&gt;First, it's all OpenType&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that most people don't know is that both TTF and OTF font are &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/typography/otspec/"&gt;OpenType fonts&lt;/a&gt;. OpenType is a binary format, with an open specification (i.e. it's free to implement codecs for, and you can sign up for the opentype mailing list and influence future versions), that contains outline data (for drawing letters), tons of metadata used for things ranging from typesetting to hardware memory management, and language-specific typesetting rules like contextual substitutions and positioning. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people talk about "TTF" or "OTF" what they really mean is "files that end in &lt;code&gt;.ttf&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.otf&lt;/code&gt;", and those are two kinds of OpenType font: fonts ending in &lt;code&gt;.ttf&lt;/code&gt; are generally OpenType fonts that use the glyf/loca data blocks, with &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/Typography/SpecificationsOverview.aspx"&gt;"TrueType"&lt;/a&gt; outlines, whereas fonts ending in &lt;code&gt;.otf&lt;/code&gt; are OpenType fonts that use a &lt;a href="https://partners.adobe.com/public/developer/en/font/5176.CFF.pdf"&gt;CFF data block&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href="https://partners.adobe.com/public/developer/en/font/5177.Type2.pdf"&gt;"Type2"&lt;/a&gt; outlines. So the difference is in the outline language used. Everything else is the same, and there's a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of "everything else" in an OpenType font.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're not going to look at all the fine differences between the two in this post, but let's look at the ones that are easy to talk about and already make a big difference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="truetype-tiny-simple-and-hardcoded-hinting"&gt;TrueType - tiny, simple, and hardcoded hinting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TrueType outlines are incredibly straight forward: you get lines and &lt;a href="http://pomax.github.io/bezierinfo/#introduction"&gt;quadratic curves&lt;/a&gt;, and that's pretty much it. It's really easy to define shapes in, but the curves are "too" simple so you need quite a few of them. If you have decent design tool, that's mostly irrelevant, and the only thing you'll notice is that an OpenType font that uses TrueType outlines tends to be bigger than an OpenType font with Type2 outlines for the same shapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other way in which TrueType differs is in how &lt;a href="https://www.typotheque.com/articles/hinting"&gt;"hinting"&lt;/a&gt; works. Hinting is a mechanism to tell font engines "if you need to scale this outline down to fit in the font size we need, and that leads to weird sub pixel positioning, here's how you should resolve that:..." When using TrueType, the hinting is explicit: all the information is stored in the TrueType data, so a font engine can be "dumb" about hinting and simply do what the font tells it to. That makes TrueType, again, a little bigger compared to Type2, but taken together with the simplicity of the language means it's really easy for people to write parsers that do the right thing. Not a lot of instructions, and the hinting is in-font.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Although even then, hinting can go &lt;a href="http://www.rastertragedy.com/"&gt;terribly wrong&lt;/a&gt;, because it's an incredibly hard subject)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="type2-rich-complicated-and-only-hinted-"&gt;Type2 - rich, complicated, and "only" hinted.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the Type2 language is super rich, with lots of nuanced outline operations possible (including some 'if humans can tell this is gently curve, curve it, otherwise make this a flat line" instructions!), as well as supporting a small programming language that lets you do some amazing things... if the font engine that's rendering the font supports them. Because most of them don't: Type2 supports lines and cubic curves, and these are generally supported by font engines, but they also support more esoteric operations that a lot of font engines simply don't bother to support. That is unfortunate, and hopefully that will change as time goes on, but right now that's how it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make matters worse, the hinting in a Type2 outline is really "just hints". Type2 outlines can mark certain edges and points as needing to line up in some way, but it is up to the font engine to make sure that "lining up" happens sensibly, and (again because this is not a trivial task) a lot of font engines just ... don't bother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads people who are used to working with software that comes with a simple, or incomplete, font engine to claim that TTF is better than OTF because they look better, even though they don't: it's just the font engine not being good enough to deal with the space-optimised Type2 outline language, rather than the simplistic but "everything up front" TrueType outline language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-which-should-i-use-"&gt;"Which should I use?"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real question tends to be which format you should use. If you're  a typeface designer, or a font engineer, I don't have to tell you which is to use, you already know the answer based on what you need to make, but if you're a font &lt;strong&gt;user&lt;/strong&gt;, which should you use? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It depends entirely on what's available, and which engine you're going to use. If the font (or, font family) you want to use is only available in &lt;code&gt;.otf&lt;/code&gt; form, and you're going to use it in an excellent font engine like Adobe's own engine, then clearly: pick &lt;code&gt;.otf&lt;/code&gt;. If, on the other hand, you want a font that works best on the web, then it's really a toss-up between &lt;code&gt;.ttf&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.otf&lt;/code&gt; and the only real answer is "try them both, and see which one looks best". It might even be that at low point sizes the &lt;code&gt;.ttf&lt;/code&gt; looks best, but at higher point sizes, the &lt;code&gt;.otf&lt;/code&gt; looks better. If they're small fonts (i.e. the size of a JPEG image, which most fonts comfortably fall under) then why not just use both?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="more-to-come"&gt;More to come&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to just get these posts out I'm going to keep some of them short, and this is one of the shorter ones, but rest assured that there's a lot to say about OpenType fonts, including how little most people know about them. And that's not an indictment, unless it's people espousing the virtue of one over the other without even realising they're both just OpenType fonts, only differing in the outline language, which is a large part of, but most certainly not the definitive aspect of, modern fonts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next time I'll try to go into that statement a bit more: modern OpenType fonts are pretty dang complex pieces of software, and you could take the outline shapes for granted and still have a lot of amazingly detailed and rich data left to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Fonts</category>
<category>OpenType</category>
<category>TrueType</category>
<category>Type2</category>
<category>TTF</category>
<category>OTF</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1449438115186</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1449438115186</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 21:41:55 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> Github broke my blog, so I had to reset it...</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Github is usually pretty good when it comes to gh-pages and github.io hosting, but for some reason, an update to my pomax.github.io repository had broken whatever it is that github does when it deploys websites, to the point where even deleting my repository and then rebuilding it made things simply "not work".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up completely resetting the repository, which meant deleting it, which means all comments ever left by people are gone (I'm very sorry about that, thankfully the important thing about them was our conversation, not the historical record of that conversastion), and it turns out that github broke on the "gh-weblog" directory in the filessystem.  Renaming it to "gh-weblog-2" made things magically work (and boy do I wish I'd tried that first now, obviously), but creating a new dir "gh-weblog" and dropping files in there will land them into the repo, but keep them inaccesssisble on the github.io site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you were wondering where my articles had gone on Saturday, December 5th, now you know =(&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Github</category>
<category>Blog</category>
<category>Rebuilds</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1449383023410</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1449383023410</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 06:23:43 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> Bezier curves are not invariant under conformal mapping</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;That's not a post title that'll sound very appealing to many people, but it's a question without an easy-to-google answer that I get asked more often than makes sense to keep answering on a case by case basis. So let me turn it into a URL on the internet instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invariance is defined as "any operation you can apply to the control points that define a Bezier curve, and then forming the curve, will yield the same curve as if you broke up the curve as a  sequence of individual points, and applied that operation to each of those, separately".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bezier curves are invariant under &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affine_transformation"&gt;affine linear transforms&lt;/a&gt;, which are those transforms that preserve parallel lines, but not necessarily distance between points or angles between lines. Basic affine linear transforms &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_map#Examples_of_linear_transformation_matrices"&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; rotation, reflection, translation, shearing, scaling, and projection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this is not the only class of transforms (obviously), and another transform that people tend to be interested in are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conformal_map"&gt;conformal mappings&lt;/a&gt;, which preserve the (local) angle between lines, and this is a problem for Bezier curves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest conformal mapping I can think of is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_tilings_in_hyperbolic_plane"&gt;hyperbolic tiling&lt;/a&gt;, which maps the Euclidean ("rectangular") plane onto a circle plane instead, with a neat property:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the center of the Euclidean plane is the center of the circle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;draw a line from the center, outward to infinity; this is a straight line in both the Euclidean plane and on the circle, but:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a point along that line at distance D from the center of the Euclidean plane will lie at some distance D'&amp;lt;D from the "center" of the circle, and,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;any point along that line at twice the distance, E = 2D, on the Euclidean plane will lie on distance E' &amp;lt; 2D' - that is, outward travel at constant speed in the Euclidean plane, covering infinite distance, turns into monotone decreasing travel in terms of speed and distance, covering finite distance: you will never cross the "edge" of the circle, you just keep going slower and slower as you get closer and closer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are an infinite number of functions that achieve this kind of mapping, but all of them preserve local angles: If two straight lines crossed each other at 37 degrees on the Euclidean plane, then the lines themselves will no longer be straight, but at the exact point of their intersection, the angle between them will still be 37 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you conformally map  the points that define a Bezier curve, and then draw a new curve with those mapped points, you are not guaranteed to get the same curve as if you'd treated the curve a sequence of points that together draw the curve, and then conformally mapped all of those instead. And we can prove this with a single example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A mapping that turns straight lines into circular arcs is a conformal mapping, preserving local angles of intersection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bezier curves can perfectly represent straight lines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bezier curves cannot perfectly represent circular arcs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This mapping will turn geometry that can be represented by Bezier curves into geometry that cannot be represented by Bezier curves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Q.E.D."&gt;QED&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to think about this is that Bezier curves are formed using (iterated) linear interpolation, which relies on straight lines staying linear. If we deform them to some non-linear form, then we cannot use linear interpolation and still find the same resulting points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there you have it. Are Bezier curves invariant under conformal mapping? No, they are not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Maths</category>
<category>Bezier Curves</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1449335750620</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1449335750620</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 17:15:50 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> "Tell me what some of your strengths are..."</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I attended a work seminar on discovering your personal strengths and how to identify and curtail stress behaviour. Let me just give the summary first:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it was incredibly useful, and I'd urge you to do something similar if you haven't yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="know-yourself"&gt;Know yourself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main point is to learn what you're good at, so that you can focus your efforts into further developing skills that fall in categories related to where you are at your strongest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you might like doing a million different things, but if you really want to develop yourself, find out which few you're really going to be good at, and exploit that. Not necessarily give up on the others, just make sure you &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt; on the ones that really come to you naturally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, know how you react when you get driven into a corner. Some of us are naturals at personal development, most of us are not, and the great thing about attending a seminar like this is that you get exposed to some of the psychology behind a few major generic personalities. For instance, here's my list of "strengths", spread over two categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategic thinking:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input: "you crave to know more, and like to collect information and archive it". &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learner: "you have a great desire to learn and continuously improve. In particular, learning, rather than the outcome, excites you".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intellection: "you are characterized by your intellectual activity. you're introspective, and appreciate intellectual discussions". &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relationship building:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relator: "you enjoy building close relationships, and find deep satisfaction in working hard with friends to achieve goals".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connectedness: "you think all things are connected and don't believe in coincidence. almost every event has a reason".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here's the thing: based on their simple definitions, not all of these strengths make a lot of sense. Thankfully, there are individualised descriptions of what each of these strengths mean, and so things start to make a lot more sense, and rather than "fortune cookie" information, one can actually learn something meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="meaningful-descriptors"&gt;Meaningful descriptors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seminar I attended used the &lt;a href="http://strengths.gallup.com/110440/About-StrengthsFinder-20.aspx"&gt;Clifton Strengthsfinder 2.0&lt;/a&gt; test, based on data by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallup_%28company%29"&gt;Gallup&lt;/a&gt; gathered over quite a few years from over 100,000 participants. I like science, and if this data is going to say something "about me", then that's at least a decent sample size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, of course the predictions won't be perfect, but it'll be good enough to act as starting point to acknowledge your own strengths and personality type, and exploit the strengths while working on minimizing the reactionary tendencies. So: who am I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="strategic-thinking-input"&gt;Strategic thinking: Input&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like information. I like learning new things, and learning &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; new things, but I don't particularly care about archiving, because I trust my brain to do that for me without having to bother with it. So what does "input" really mean? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are good that you can simplify the most complex, convoluted, or intricate procedure. People usually rely on you to offer clear and easy-to-comprehend explanations. Driven by your talents, you may notice that certain people turn to you for guidance. Maybe your willingness to share the knowledge you have gained over the years partially explains the fondness they have for you. Some individuals might have benefited from what you have read, observed, or experienced. It’s very likely that you frequently use academic-sounding words to talk about your ideas or areas of expertise. You intentionally spend time broadening your vocabulary by looking up words in the dictionary and committing their meanings to memory. By nature, you occasionally combine your fascination for reading with your ability to figure out what sets specific individuals apart from everyone else. You might discover the things that interest someone. Then you may read more about these topics. Perhaps you aim to collect insights that inspire the person to take advantage of his or her one-of-akind talents, knowledge, and/or skills. Because of your strengths, you might gather ideas and information from reading publications that keep you up to date on particular types of current events. What you choose to peruse — that is, examine studiously — may reflect some of your personal or professional interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes a bit more sense than the generic summary. It also offers far more footholds when it comes to aspects of this strength that can be relied or built on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="strategic-thinking-learner"&gt;Strategic thinking: Learner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't lie: I liked seeing this strength. I do very much enjoy learning new things, and seeing this as one of my strengths was basically one of those "yep, I knew it" moments. However, "I like to learn new things" is a pretty generic strength, so seeing the much bigger analysis was quite useful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instinctively, you endorse the importance of acquiring additional knowledge and gaining new skills. You regard education as an ongoing activity. It’s very likely that you occasionally collect bits and pieces of information. At the time, the value of this material may not be apparent. In specific cases, you have found it useful to turn to some specialists for help. Perhaps these individuals can provide you with enough direction so you can ask some questions, render a few decisions, or try to map courses of action without upsetting anyone in the process. You avoid angering certain people by consulting with them before doing anything. Driven by your talents, you may long to gather certain types of information about specific individuals. Perhaps your “need to know” is rarely satisfied. The more facts you gather, the easier it might be for you to understand someone’s strengths, limitations, interests, likes, dislikes, or goals. You might be inclined to study human beings one by one. To some degree, your ongoing observations of selected individuals provide you with interesting insights into human nature. By nature, you intentionally include uncommon, highly technical, or sophisticated words in your vocabulary. You realize that language is a form of knowledge that gives you an upper hand — that is, controlling power — in conversations, debates, or discussions. It quickly establishes you as an authority figure in listeners’ minds. First, you capture their attention. Then you take charge of events, projects, meetings, or problem solving. Chances are good that you may be a solo performer. You might be determined to broaden your knowledge or acquire new skills. Perhaps you are drawn to the process of education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there you have it. Pretty much all of this rings true. And yes, on their own each of these phrases sound like a horoscope, but it's not the individual phrases that form the strength, it's the collection of all of them, applicable to this person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm okay with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="strategic-thinking-intellection"&gt;Strategic thinking: Intellection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This strength feels a little weird, because it's hard to go "why yes, I am intellectual" and not come off smug. The main problem is that "intellectual" and "smart" are often treated as the same thing, and in this particular case, they're not. I could give lots of examples, but instead it just makes far more sense to let the snippets do the talking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are good that you sometimes wish you could switch off your active brain. Even so, you may enjoy your time alone as you ponder ideas. Perhaps you want to test whether they make sense. Because of your strengths, you may be selective about the types of books or publications you read. They might contain information or tips that you can share with individuals you are training. Perhaps imparting knowledge, talking about your experiences, or passing along your skills gives you a certain degree of satisfaction. By nature, you may find it easier to befriend certain types of people if they tell you what they want to accomplish. Knowing that much, you might read some books, journals, newspapers, correspondence, or Internet sites to broaden your knowledge about their interests. When you can share information that helps people move closer to their goals, perhaps you can begin to understand each other a little better. It’s very likely that you eagerly welcome opportunities to think out loud about ideas, theories, or philosophies. You derive pleasure from conversations that force you to ponder matters that exist only in the realm of thought, not in reality. Driven by your talents, you sometimes delight in having your very own tasks to perform. Perhaps you like to solo because it gives you quiet time to reflect on what you think or feel. Maybe you consider what you have done, are doing, or can do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id="relationship-building-relator"&gt;Relationship building: Relator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one confused me, because while I like deep relationships, I'm perfectly fine with shallow ones, too. The generic description didn't seem to match at all, but the detailed one certainly did:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By nature, you are naturally open and honest about who you are, what you have done, what you can do, and what you cannot do. Your straightforward explanations and stories help listeners see you as you see yourself. You reveal your strengths and limitations. You are forthright and plainspoken. People generally seek your company and want to work with you. Many are impelled to move into action by your words and examples. It’s very likely that you periodically are sought out by people whom you have befriended. They may trust you when you have taken time to know them individually. This may partially explain why certain people come back again and again for ideas or suggestions. They might realize you try to tailor your words of wisdom to fit their unique situations, needs, strengths, limitations, goals, or personalities. Driven by your talents, you may be convinced that you are measuring up to your potential. Perhaps you know when you are doing your best work or earning the highest grades you possibly can. Chances are good that you occasionally tell yourself that you are an effective mentor or trainer. Perhaps individuals benefit from the investment you make in them. Because of your strengths, you might do your best training after you become well-acquainted with someone. Perhaps you want to discover each individual’s unique talents, work style, goals, motivations, or interests. Maybe these insights tell you what suggestions to make or what tips to offer during coaching sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, this very blog post is essentially proof of how true this assessment is: I'm right now telling you about something that a lot of people would consider pretty personal, and that last bit pretty much underlines how I even started this post: learning about different personalities and strengths, and how to work with those in oneself and other people, is fascinating, as well as functionally useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="relationship-building-connectedness"&gt;Relationship Building: Connectedness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this one was a genuine surprise, at least based on the generic descriptions. It sounds very much like a "faith in the oneness of all things", which really doesn't describe my take on matters at all. I believe in a quantum universe (at least, for now. Physics is still developing), and while I don't believe in "coincidence", I also don't analyse things from just one perspective, and so the notion of "a coincidence" doesn't even make sense to me. There are so many different perspectives on single events that are all simultaneously in effect that even if you'd pretend there was a coincidence in one of those, that same coincidence would vanish in others. This strength felt like nonsense. But then this more personalised description actually made it make sense:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By nature, you may get to know people individually in your quest to gain wisdom. Discovering the qualities that distinguish someone from everyone else might be an essential aspect of your search for truth. Driven by your talents, you might be fascinated with certain ideas, policies, or philosophies that affect human beings around the world. Because of your strengths, you may be able to accept unpredictable events in your life on the basis of sheer faith. Perhaps you sense there is a force greater than you at work in the world. Occasionally you can live with not knowing the exact reason why something good or bad happened to you and not to someone else. Chances are good that you sometimes think like a detective. You might search for and find obvious and not-so-obvious clues. You might determine which ones link together. Now and then, you notice gaps in your investigation. Some of these cannot be explained using reason alone. You may feel comfortable accepting what is unknown and unknowable. Why? To some extent, you trust that everything, everyone, and every action is somehow intertwined. Instinctively, you may be determined to make the acquaintance of certain individuals you identify as seekers of truth. Perhaps you are attracted to people who ponder philosophical questions such as “What is the meaning of life?” or “What is beauty?” or “What constitutes wisdom?” or “Why do bad things happen to good people?” or “Why should ordinary people like me even ask these kinds of questions?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading this, it basically reads as a description of being a university student who's taking a masters in A.I. which happens to be exactly who I was, and whose intellectual inheritance I still live today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="weaknesses-the-reactionary-side-of-things"&gt;Weaknesses: the reactionary side of things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of the seminar, when people get put on the spot, and stressed to a breaking point, the behaviour they might display is broadly categorised in three possible ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complying: giving away the control over the situation and taking it from there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protecting: walking away from the situation to protect oneself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Controlling: going into "getting shit done" mode and steamrolling anyone who doesn't do so as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are just words with short descriptors, and people often enough display more than one type of behaviour, depending on the situation. However, I know myself reasonably well in this respect, and I'm virtually always protecting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will turn off any emotional attachment, and deal with problems in what is best described as "the vulcan way". I've certainly been abrasively critical in the past often enough for it to rub people the wrong way, and I've been trying to get better at &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; being abrasive, but a seminar like this is a great supplement to introspection: it puts what you sort of already thought into a wider perspective, and most importantly gives you insight into how the way you behave under stress will affect others who are also operating under stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I'm stressed, and the person I'm dealing with is stressed as well (and for whatever reason. Not strictly work), then if they're of a complying nature, we're going to have problems. Because they'll want a resolution, and I'll be offering criticism without solutions. That won't get us anywhere, except "more stuck". Similarly, if they're controlling, they'll be coming up with what solution works, and I'll just shoot it right back down. And that's just the "practical" result, emotionally there's a lot of potential for resentment both ways, and things can get very nasty. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-so-tell-us-some-of-your-strengths-"&gt;"So tell us some of your strengths..."&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know that question you get at job interviews, where they want to know what your strengths and weaknesses are? This is what they're talking about. This is why I'd recommend everyone to take a seminar like this even if you're between jobs, or even if you've yet to start on your first one. There's "knowing what you're good at", and there's "knowing the strengths that you can build on and exploit", and they're two different things. The first most people develop naturally, by virtue of just doing what they do. The second, everyone can use some help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also lets you know what you're not. That sounds a little weird, because there's an infinite world of infinite possibilities out there, but there're broadly speaking four categories of personalities and strengths that you want as part of an effective team, and a team made entirely of "learners" isn't going to be very useful. Fun, probably, but not something that makes business sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fall in the strategic thinking and relationship building categories. That means that if I'm put on a team, my contribution plays off of having other people with different skills: people with execution skills to keep us on track and meet deadlines, and people with influence skills to get the most out of all the team members as well as facilitate negotiations within the team. Also, having a good spread of different "reactionary" behaviours helps to make sure no one "agrees to be stuck in a rut". Obviously no one likes being stuck, but if we're all the same kind of reactionaries, things go real bad, real fast. Much faster than if there's a good spread.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-take-home-message"&gt;The take-home message&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the take-home message from this seminar was that it's really useful to do a thing like this at least once, even if you don't have a job right now, or you think you know yourself: if you've never done a personal strengths test before then chances are good you think you know what you're good at, and you might know what makes your temper-self so problematic, but there is great value in seeing things affirmed, or even being shown that there are parts of you that you never thought about, but ring very close to home: knowing yourself is not just something that helps you, it also helps others work, or just be, with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been paired up with a "buddy", and we'll be holding each other accountable for the action plan we've drawn up on how to work on our weaknesses while also trying to focus on what we think are our most exploitable strengths. That probably sounds pretty lame, but at the same time, it's two people being committed to helping each other better themselves in a "no judging" relationship.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a pretty sweet outcome for a seminar called "Leadership Discovery".&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Mozilla</category>
<category>Leadership</category>
<category>Strengths</category>
<category>Introspection</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1442796369118</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1442796369118</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 00:46:09 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> Mozilla released a tool I am excited about.</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tl,dr&lt;/strong&gt;: you should have a look at &lt;a href="https://thimble.mozilla.org"&gt;https://thimble.mozilla.org&lt;/a&gt;, and if you think "this is just a fancy jsbin", challenge yourself to first read &lt;a href="http://blog.humphd.org/thimble-and-bramble"&gt;http://blog.humphd.org/thimble-and-bramble&lt;/a&gt;, which explains in detail how this is nothing like the other "single tool sites" we had on the web until pretty much this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, Thimble has a larger story here for me, personally, and I'd like to tell you that story so that you might understand why I am genuinely excited about this tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="once-upon-a-time-i-was-a-java-developer-"&gt;Once upon a time, I was a Java developer.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a round-about way, my first "being a programmer" identity started in University. As a kid I'd written things in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BASIC"&gt;Basic&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turbo_Pascal"&gt;Turbo Pascal&lt;/a&gt;, but it wasn't until University that I was taught how to write structured programs that were more than utilities or silly time wasters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first "real programming" kicked in about three years into &lt;a href="http://gss.uva.nl/future-msc-students/information-sciences/content26/artificial-intelligence.html"&gt;my AI education&lt;/a&gt;, when we were taking a 10 credit course that involved working on real world AI applications, I worked on a java code base for running distributed sensors backed by software agents that collaborated on performing Bayesian reasoning about signal sources. It was interesting, and after the course was done, landed me my first student job continuing my work on it. I ended up designing the code architecture, which ended up landing me my first permanent job, and ultimately gave me a subject I could do a master's thesis on (yes, that's the order things happened in).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course I was still programming my own things in my spare time, as well as maintaining some websites (most notably &lt;a href="http://nihongoresources.com"&gt;nihongoresources.com&lt;/a&gt;) and when a friend mentioned doing some log visualisations using a language called &lt;a href="http://processing.org"&gt;"Processing"&lt;/a&gt; (which is the worst name for a programming language that wants to be searchable on the internet btw), I figured I'd have a look at what this mystery language was. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turned out, I really liked Processing: it was &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; Java, but with more freedom: a simpler modeling concept, "global unless you enclose it" functions, immediate execution of code in an imperfect editor (the "PDE") that was good enough to write quick, super sweet visual things. What's more there was even a JavaScript port available, for running your pde files online. Not as Java Applets, but just "as content". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up using Processing enough that I started running into annoying inconsistencies, or even bugs, in the &lt;a href="http://processingjs.org"&gt;Processing.js&lt;/a&gt; port, and being familiar with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Relay_Chat"&gt;IRC&lt;/a&gt; I jumped into the #processing.js channel on irc.mozilla.org and started complaining whenever things didn't work. In some places, that gets you kicked out of a channel, but in this one, a user called "&lt;a href="http://blog.humphd.org"&gt;humph&lt;/a&gt;" flipped my complaints around and threw them back at me as suggestions on how bugs could be filed, discussed, and fixed, instead. Without knowing it, I was getting a lesson in how to be a member of a community, and it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My life in today's definition of open source really started there: I started filing bugs, I knew JavaScript well enough to write code for web pages, but the kind of JS needed to write Processing.js was different, so I started learning more about JS as I tried to figure out problems in Processing.js, and at some point decided I knew enough that I could patch problems when I ran into them, with a community of devs that were kind enough to help me through the process of getting those patches submitted and landed into the main codebase. I ended up, I think it's fair to say, a major contributor to Processing.js, I moved from the Netherlands to Canada and went from Java developer to freelance web dev with a love of JS, and that's where this story turns into my involvement with Mozilla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-i-want-to-put-a-team-together-"&gt;"I want to put a team together."&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't talk about humph, or really, Dave Humphrey, without a certain amount of adoration (and that is a well-considered word).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't heard of Dave, he's a Professor of Open Source with ties to Mozilla, teaching at &lt;a href="http://cdot.senecacollege.ca"&gt;CDOT&lt;/a&gt;, at &lt;a href="http://www.senecacollege.ca"&gt;Seneca College&lt;/a&gt; in Toronto, and if you use Firefox, there's a good chance you've enjoyed his work. Dave, to me, is in the category of people who look at something and go "what, 2 years from now, is a thing I want to be taking for granted as available and usable, that isn't there right now". And then, unlike many people, doesn't just blog about it, but sits down and figures out how to make it happen. The part that earns him my adoration is that one of his approaches is to inspire others to do the work, because he has the singular ability to explain his ideas in ways that hold up, and make you excited about the prospect of them becoming reality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he was thinking of "a thing" that would require getting some people together to make it happen. Needless to say, he had my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dave had been linking me to &lt;a href="http://marksurman.commons.ca/blog"&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; about making the web about "making" instead of "consuming" by a guy called "Mark Surman" every now and then, and while I'd never heard of the man, his posts made a lot of sense. It wasn't until Dave explain his idea to me that things clicked: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Surman"&gt;Mark Surman&lt;/a&gt; was the director of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozilla_Foundation"&gt;Mozilla Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, and the idea that Dave had was a project to foster "making on the web" through a Mozilla Foundation initiative that you might have heard of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"&lt;a href="https://webmaker.org"&gt;Webmaker&lt;/a&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="in-2012-i-joined-a-tiny-mozilla-foundation-"&gt;In 2012, I joined a tiny Mozilla Foundation.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I applied to the Mozilla Foundation as a software engineer when it was pretty small. Certainly not "5 people and a goat" levels of small, but when I joined, &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/staff/ryan"&gt;Ryan Merkley&lt;/a&gt; was still with the foundation with the explicit goal of growing it to self-sustaining size, and while I had initially expected to work on "Popcorn Maker", an online video mashup/remixing tool spearheaded by the fascinating &lt;a href="http://www.etherworks.ca"&gt;Brett Gaylor&lt;/a&gt; (from &lt;a href="http://donottrack.us"&gt;Do Not Track&lt;/a&gt; fame), I instead ended up working on a project that was about letting people write HTML in a friendly way, to allow them to learn HTML while also making things they wanted to make on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For quite a few months there was no name, and initially the "webmaker" name applied only to this particular tool, but as we folded more tools into the offering (popcorn maker and the "x-ray goggles", most notably), the overarching program became "Webmaker", and the tool that I was involved with became "Thimble". It was an interesting thing to work on: I learned a ton about patterns and antipatterns in the JavaScript world, and despite the tool being a single page editor, people responded positively. Thimble empowered people on the web in a way that they hadn't been until then, and that made it really important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as a developer, I wouldn't use it myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same way that I won't do my job using &lt;a href="http://jsbin.com"&gt;jsbin&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://jsfiddle.net"&gt;jsfiddle&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://codepen.io"&gt;codepen&lt;/a&gt; as &lt;em&gt;tools&lt;/em&gt;, Thimble was too simple to address the needs of "everyone". It was great for sitting down to &lt;em&gt;with someone&lt;/em&gt;, and running them through a "zero to hero!" process where they walked away from the experience with the ability to create simple HTML pages for their own, personal content, and a way to put that content on the web (outside of social media postings), but there was no reason to ever use it if you already knew HTML and CSS and JS, and certainly not if you were a developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="thimble-got-upgraded-quite-a-bit-"&gt;Thimble got upgraded quite a bit...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a year of Thimble, as well as several other tools being part of the Webmaker offering, we made a decision to give a new technology called &lt;a href="http://nodejs.org"&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt; a shot at the Foundation. As a JavaScript server side technology, it offered the benefits of "the same language everywhere", rather than the "JS in the browser, Python on the server" that we'd been using until then, and we quickly learned how to use Node.js and &lt;a href="http://expressjs.com"&gt;Express&lt;/a&gt; (in no small part thanks to colleague and friend jbuck, who did a phenomenal job at giving an hour and a half lecture on how to go from an empty file to a fully functional Express server, following best practices), and in the process rewrote parts of our tools to take advantage of the fact that everything could be done in JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were able to add features and fix bugs much quicker than before, and we ended up releasing updates almost as fast as we could land bugs. But the Thimble tool stayed relatively samey: yes, there was progressively better support for error reporting in HTML and CSS, and we figured out how to safely allow script execution, so that people could write "real" web pages, but they were still just single pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the help of &lt;a href="http://thomaspark.co"&gt;Tom Park&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://drexel.edu"&gt;Drexel University&lt;/a&gt; we came up with a way to present not just an editor but also a tutorial system, so that using Thimble for educational purposes would be easier, but ultimately it was still just single pages. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="this-was-not-a-tool-that-would-work-for-everyone-"&gt;This was not a tool that would work for everyone.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with Thimble, and I'm making it sound like one but for the purpose of Thimble it mostly wasn't, was that it was aimed at an audience that I wasn't part of. In my professional life, I could do everything Thimble did, better, in tools I already had at my disposal on my computers. A desktop code editor and a browser gave me more power than the single flat file concept Thimble operated on, and so I would still use Thimble to teach people, but that was it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were always ideas. "Wouldn't it be great if Thimble was like a real editor, but friendly when it needed to be, while being progressively less 'teaching tool' and more a real development tool as you level up your skills". It &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; be great. But we couldn't make that tool. Having the tool work for educational setting was more important than spending time on making it better for a group of people who already had tools at their disposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes sense, and that makes what makes the end of this story even more remarkable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="atom-brackets-and-thimble-oh-my-"&gt;Atom, Brackets, and Thimble; Oh my!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sever-side JavaScript did more than just skyrocket Node.js's popularity: it also allowed for some "chromeless" browser experiments ("chrome" not just being the name of Google's browser, but in the browser world also being the name for every part of the the browser's interface that isn't "the part that shows you the webpages". The term was in already widely used when Google appropriated it) which ended up spawning "pure JS" code editors. Code editors called &lt;a href="https://atom.io"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://brackets.io"&gt;Brackets&lt;/a&gt; hit the scene, being experiments on using a chromeless browser as a UI framework, and using pure JS as the editor engine. Presented as normal desktop applications, but "powered by the web", there was a lot of love for these new flavours of code editors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But: if they ran in a headless browser, there wasn't any real reason why they shouldn't be able to, at least in principal, run in real browsers, online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's where Dave showed his genius: he took Adobe's "Brackets" editor, and at &lt;a href="http://2013.mozillafestival.org"&gt;MozFest 2013&lt;/a&gt; showed off that it might be possible to put it in the browser, and use it as the code editing part of Thimble, rather than relying on &lt;a href="https://codemirror.net"&gt;codemirror&lt;/a&gt;, so that people would have all the power of a true code editor at their disposal. There was a confluence of technologies that he knew of that could take "making things on the web" to a whole new level, and listening to him describe it, it was the kind of thing I wanted to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine opening a code editor with file management, running a localhost server for proper &lt;code&gt;http://&lt;/code&gt; protocol testing, and a browser with live reloading so you could see the results instantly. As a dev, that sounds a lot like how I do my work already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now imagine not doing those things separately because the browser just does &lt;em&gt;all those things&lt;/em&gt;. A true file system, a true code editor, a true zero-conf HTTP server, true live reloading, all of it, just working. No questions asked. Start it up, and it all just... works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, that's the future. And that's what Dave was suggesting was possible. If we could put in the time to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sometimes-tough-choices-aren-t-fun"&gt;Sometimes, tough choices aren't fun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, we didn't have the man hours to make that happen. I really, really loved the idea, but we didn't have the time or the people to stop working on Webmaker, and the Thimble we already had, and instead work on this new thing. This made me sad: it felt like we were focusing on the wrong things by sticking with the Thimble we had. Imagine growing up in a country rife with corruption, and discovering "Norway" is a real thing: while Thimble was still the same tool it had been before, I had seen a glimpse of what it &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be, and how much better that was, and simply knowing that the technology allowed for this amazing thing, devalued the Thimble we worked on for me, instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the Mozilla Foundation is about fostering a "maker attitude" on the web, and promoting digital literacy, not "maintaining a set of tools in perpetuity" and even though Thimble was a tool that helped people express themselves creatively on the web, while learning about how the web works, we were constantly looking at what else we could do, or what we could do instead, to instill those core ideas in people, but not necessarily with the same tools all the time. We came up with Appmaker, which allowed people to make web apps, using web technologies - it was fun, it ended up not working as well as we'd hoped, and so we tried something else. We took the lessons we learned and made a page builder that used templates to allow people to make simple pages that also worked as apps on platforms that supported WebApps (like Android and Firefox OS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We looked at the world, and saw a significant part of the world experiencing massive friction between "what the web can do", and "how it was experienced": over a billion people are slowly coming online all over the world right now (even in places like Europe or the US), and the only "internet" they get is through preinstalled apps on their phone; they use Facebook, Twitter, Instagram, but not a browser, that supposedly ubiquitous gateway to the world wide web. The browser is supposed to open up the whole wide world to you, whereas branded apps like Facebook's client are like the CompuServe and AOL of days gone by; you get content presented in one way. Their way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a good thing, and so we changed what the app we made could do, transforming it into an &lt;a href="https://beta.webmaker.org"&gt;Android app&lt;/a&gt; (available in the &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.mozilla.webmaker"&gt;Play Store&lt;/a&gt; for free) that lets you build simple multi-view websites with text, images, and navigation buttons, to cater to the needs of the people we talked to in the various countries in the world where internet connectivity is starting to boom. It's not done, but the response from people for whom the app makes sense because they've been getting, effectively, locked-in devices has been great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we deprecated the tools we had been using for the last few years, &lt;a href="https://blog.webmaker.org/whats-next-for-webmaker-tools"&gt;moving some to new homes and retiring others&lt;/a&gt;. And that's where this story comes full circle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We killed off Thimble. And replaced it with Thimble.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="letting-others-do-the-work-you-can-t"&gt;Letting others do the work you can't&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to borrow a page out of Dave's book, and profess my enthusiasm for the "let others do the work when you can't do it" doctrine, even though it's a bit of a boomerang: while we were doing all this at the Mozilla Foundation, various people were working on the various technologies that could be glued together as the kind of vision-of-the-future Thimble that Dave had talked about in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/modeswitch"&gt;Alan Kligman&lt;/a&gt; developed a &lt;a href="https://github.com/filerjs/filer"&gt;POSIX filesystem&lt;/a&gt; that ran on top of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indexed_Database_API"&gt;IndexDB&lt;/a&gt;, Dave had been working on getting Brackets itself to &lt;a href="https://github.com/humphd/brackets/tree/bramble"&gt;work in the browser&lt;/a&gt;, the web itself had landed, or had in draft, several new technologies that made data management and communication between processes, documents, and service workers easier, and eventually everything was available for Dave to put together a team of students and see if they could combine everything into the kind of Thimble I had been hoping for since Dave showed me Brackets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, August 31&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; 2015, that thing officially &lt;a href="http://thimble.mozilla.org"&gt;became real&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-new-thimble-is-a-dream-tool-and-i-love-it"&gt;The new Thimble is a dream tool, and I love it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a true thing: the day the new Thimble got announced, I stopped using jsbin, jsfiddle, codepen, and all those other "make a quick html/css/js thing online" tools. Overnight, they had become obsolete. Anything I used them for could be done better in the new Thimble, and where jsbin or codepen let me be creative in a "single thing", the new Thimble lets me be creative without a ceiling. It's simplified the tools necessary to have a live server running with a full file system at my fingertips to "just open thimble.mozilla.org", and I can make things as simple or as complicated as I want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a true code editor that I can use to make as many files, in as many directories, as I need to properly organize and work on my code. There is undo/redo, but I don't ever have to hit save: my changes are synced by the extremely clever file system that Thimble runs on top of. It has an invisible zero-conf webserver running &lt;em&gt;in the browser&lt;/em&gt; that shows me the result of what I'm writing right next to the content I'm working on. I no longer need a live-server or a &lt;code&gt;python -m SimpleHTTPServer&lt;/code&gt; anymore, it's all &lt;em&gt;just there&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here's a thing I didn't even think I would say as a developer: thanks to the new Thimble just... working, I don't even &lt;em&gt;need git&lt;/em&gt; anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, I don't get revision control (though really, "I don't get revision control &lt;strong&gt;yet&lt;/strong&gt;", because remember that the current &lt;a href="https://thimble.mozilla.org"&gt;https://thimble.mozilla.org&lt;/a&gt; is really just a Minimum Viable Product launch: we've only just begun to see what it can do, and now is that time to start dreaming about fancy features), but I can write my code, publish it to the web for free, and have people be able to see the code I used because they can click a button to fire up thimble with my project loaded up as a forked copy for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I just want to write some Proof of Concept code, or demonstrator code for an article I'm writing, or example code for something I'm explaining to someone online that might be useful later on, I don't need to set up a git repo, with a &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch. I can just work in Thimble, hit "publish" (which will update what is online if I'm republishing the same project, with changes) and move my attention elsewhere in the knowledge that my stuff's been updated online for everyone to play with, and my code's safe and sound on a Mozilla server somewhere. And any time I want to dive "deeper", I can just tell Thimble to export my entire filesystem as a .zip file, and then do whatever I feel I need to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The new Thimble is taking away the need for tools I thought were essential in my life.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly think that's the most impactful statement I can make here. Thimble is solving problems I didn't know I had, and that makes me super happy, and excited about the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="so-in-conclusion-"&gt;So, in conclusion:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go try out the new &lt;a href="https://thimble.mozilla.org"&gt;https://thimble.mozilla.org&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/thimble.webmaker.org/issues"&gt;let the team know what you think of it&lt;/a&gt;, and what you can imagine as, in the future, being obvious things you already use it for, that it can't do today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, and I need to be off to write code for my next blog post on writing fonts as source code. I already have Thimble open in another tab with demonstrator code doing amazing things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Mozilla</category>
<category>Thimble</category>
<category>HTML</category>
<category>CSS</category>
<category>JS</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1442700129236</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1442700129236</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2015 22:02:09 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> Making traditional French bread: baguettes</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This post is based on the original album over at &lt;a href="http://imgur.com/gallery/hQRaL"&gt;http://imgur.com/gallery/hQRaL&lt;/a&gt;, which after some requests I am reposting here for those who do not visit &lt;a href="http://imgur.com"&gt;imgur.com&lt;/a&gt;, or feel uncomfortable linking people to imgur albums. This article covers the process of making traditional baguettes from start to finish using a high hydration dough (69.5%), and cold fermentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="let-s-make-this-"&gt;Let's make this:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread.jpg" alt="Traditional french bread"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(or at least, let's make the bread part. This post is not about how to make pepper pâté, salame calabrese, or firm cheese)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll be making "pain de Tradition Française", traditional French bread; specifically, something the French would call &lt;a href="https://encrypted.google.com/search?q=baguette%20de%20campagne&amp;amp;tbs=imgo:1"&gt;"baguette de campagne"&lt;/a&gt;, not to be confused with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pain_de_campagne"&gt;"pain de campagne"&lt;/a&gt;, which is a rather different bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, "traditional" in French baking is not about a bread being "rustic" or "artisinal", it is a technical term that indicates that it has been made using only the four permitted ingredients for traditional breads: flour, water, plain salt, and yeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach we're taking here uses an extremely high hydration dough (almost 70%) and takes about an hour to make, over 2 days: we'll need about 15 minutes on day 1 to make the initial dough, which then undergoes cold fermentation (also called retarded fermentation, or delayed fermentation) in the fridge overnight, and then the next morning (or afternoon depending on how much you like to sleep in) we need about 15 minutes in the morning to prep loaves, then a 2 hour period of doing nothing while the dough rises, and then 20~30 minutes to bake the loaves into tasty, tasty bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, not important to know, with the measurements used in this post we will be making four baguettes of around 280g each. We will be using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;680 grams of all purpose flour, acting as our 100% weight metric. I use &lt;a href="http://www.robinhood.ca/Products/All-Purpose-Flours/Original-All-Purpose-Flour"&gt;Robin Hood all purpose flour&lt;/a&gt;, which is a great flour for making baguettes because it has a high protein content (around 12%), which is important if we want enough gluten formation to get good oven spring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;69.5% water (473 grams)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1.2% plain table salt (a smidge over 8 grams)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0.45% active dry yeast (3 grams)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will yield four baguettes, weighing in at  280 to 290 gram each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="day-1-making-dough-15m-"&gt;Day 1: making dough (15m)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-01.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start with 340 grams of flour, which is about 3 cups, but not every cup of flour weighs the same, so let's go with weight measurements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-02.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the flour we add about 3/4th of a tablespoon of salt, which is somewhere between 8 and 9 grams (it's hard to weigh salt if your scales only do 1 gram increments). Make sure to mix this in a little, instead of just sprinkling it on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note we really do want plain salt. If your salt has an "ingredients" list, and it contains more than "sodium chloride", like preservatives, or potassium chloride (known in Europe as Kalium Chloride, KaCl), we don't want to use that. Thankfully, pure table salt is stupidly easy to come by, and any supermarket will sell 2kg boxes of the stuff for under $10, which will last you years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-03.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of water, we're adding two cups: 470 grams (473 if you want to be super technical)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-04.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;next up: yeast. 1 teaspoon of active dry yeast, or about 3 grams. We want to dissolve this in the water before doing any mixing. It'll take a bit to dissolve properly: if we don't wait long enough, there will be some undissolved sludge left after we pour out the water. We want that sludge in the dough, not stuck to the bottom of our measuring cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-05.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the yeast's dissolved, we add all the yeasty water to the flour and salt mixture, and create what can only be properly described as "a slurry".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then mix this at a super low speed. I use a &lt;a href="http://www.overstock.com/Home-Garden/KitchenAid-KV25MEX-5.5-quart-Pro-550-Plus-Heavy-Duty-Stand-Mixer/8264907/product.html"&gt;Kitchenaid "Professional 550 Heavy Duty"&lt;/a&gt; set to 2-out-of-10, which is about the lowest you can meaningfully get, but if you're using a hand mixer, set it to the lowest speed. We want to mix the dough, not beat it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At low speed, we can basically mix for as long as we like without overworking the dough, which is important. Mixing too fast can literally destroy it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-06.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the mixer's running, we'll be adding another 340 grams (~3 cups) of flour to progressively work up the dough. We don't dump it all in at once because it'll take much longer to mix evenly, so the pictures above are after adding one cup at a time and waiting for most of the flour to be absorbed before adding the next cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-07.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once all the flour's been absorbed into the dough, the dough's not actually fully mixed yet. It'll look ragged and tear because not all the flour's hydrated, so let it run for another minute or two and it should turn into a smooth, almost paste-like consistency. It might also look "too sticky" in places (especially at the bottom, where it might look like it's terminally sludge-stuck to the bowl). Don't worry: just let the mixing do its thing for 2 minutes, the dough will homogenise. That's what mixing does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science time: when you add flour, two things happen. First, the flour is simply mixed into the dough. While that happens, the overall water content of the dough stays the same: despite having added some flour, the dough will seem just as sticky as before. The trick is that we need to wait for water to redistribute itself from "the sticky dough" to also covering the not-yet-fully-coated-in-water individual particles of flour that we just added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this process can take a minute, and that's why we'll be adding small amounts of flour at a time: if we don't wait long enough, we'll be deciding whether to add more flour while the dough's still firming up. While it might initially look right, once all the flour particles hydrate the dough will end up firmer than is desirable for this particular bread recipe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with that in mind: if after a few more minutes of mixing the dough still looks too sticky, take a quarter cup of flour, sprinkle half of that in, with the mixer on, and wait a minute. You typically only need very little to make the dough go from "sticky" to "tacky but not actually sticky", so add tiny bits of flour, let it mix in properly (not just get absorbed by the dough), and then see if the dough comes off the bowl at the bottom while mixing. If it doesn't: repeat. If it does: we're done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking the resulting dough out of the bowl (with clean, dry hands) and balling it up with two hands should now feel tacky, without actually leaving any of it sticking to your hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="night-1-low-temperature-fermentation"&gt;Night 1: Low temperature fermentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-08.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After balling up the dough, it goes into the fridge (with a pot lid as cover - they're all standard sizes, so one of your covers is bound to fit your bowl!) for a very slow, flavour developing fermentation. Note that we're not using any oil or spray to prevent the dough from sticking to the bowl. For one, oil is not used at any point in the traditional baguette process, but more importantly, if the bowl is smooth, then the dough we've just made is simply not going to stick to it. When we take it out tomorrow, it'll come out all on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I typically make this dough around noon, and then around 10pm it'll have double in size. At this stage, I take the dough out, punch it down (taking it out of the bowl and start balling it up tightly again, so all the built up gas escapes) and then it goes back into the fridge until the morning. Normally, a fresh dough like this needs maybe two hours at room temperature to double in volume. In the fridge, it takes about 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible that the dough doesn't seem to rise at all in the fridge. Rather than blaming the yeast for being dead, it is entirely possible that the fridge is cold enough for the yeast to just not "get going". In this case, we can leave the dough out of the fridge until it doubles in size, so that we know the yeast's fully activated, then punch it down and put it in the fridge. Have a look at it before going to bed, at which point it'll probably need the punching down as just described, before further developing overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="day-2-initial-shaping-15m-"&gt;Day 2: initial shaping (15m)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-09.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we take the dough out in the morning, it'll have doubled again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-10.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, again, we punch it down to its original size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-11.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we start on a 15ish minute adventure of turning the ball of dough into loaves that we will set aside to proof for an hour or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take that dough and put it on a work surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-12.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cut it up into four pieces of equal weight, and ball them up. I've covered them with a bit of flour here to make sure they don't stick (as the dough warms back it, it becomes a bit stickier), and the excess flour from that gets moved off to a little pile on the corner of my worksurface, and gets used as necessary in the next step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the measurements used, each piece'll be around 275 grams. That's 25 grams more than "real" baguette is allowed to be, but we're not selling this bread in France, and so the French laws around baguette do not apply in our house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: yes, seriously. France has laws in place to guarantee certain properties of traditional bread. Enjoy some &lt;a href="http://www.cooksinfo.com/french-bread-law-1993"&gt;http://www.cooksinfo.com/french-bread-law-1993&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-13.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we roll out the dough to about 30cm (12") sausages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than doing one piece and then moving on to the next, we roll each of them a little bit, place them aside, and then roll the next one. We do this because it gives the dough a chance to "relax" between rolls, which means you are less likely to roll the dough such that there is a huge air pocket in the middle of the dough (affectionately, as well as pejoratively, called the hole "where the baker sleeps").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We basically put a ball of dough high up on the work surface, and with two hands cupped over the dough, roll our hands down over the dough, pulling it down across the work surface as we roll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pretty much automatically starts turning our balls of dough into a fat torpedo shape after a few rolls. Once we get to stage 2, you can roll down the dough with your fingers together at the top, and then gently spreading them as you roll down, to make the dough stretch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're not aiming for speed here. I tend to do three rolls down per piece for each stage, but if you need more: go for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need fewer: you're going too fast. The dough hasn't developed to a point where it'll take the kind of forces your subjecting it to, which will make it tear internally, so slow down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-14.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the third stage we need to give the loaves one more roll-down, leaving the ends "as is", with a little more pressure in the center, to make them roughly uniform-girth sausages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, a simple trick: I like to rise my dough on parchment ("baking") paper, rather than a silicon pad, or a "baguette proofing rack" or even a couche (basically a progressive-flour-impregnated-as-it-is-used heavy linnen or burlap cloth) because it lets me use the parchment for two purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is to obviously just proof the dough without having it stick to &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. if I cut the paper to about 45cm (18") length, I can easily fold it such that will accommodate the dough as it proofs, without sticking together even all the way at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I can reuse that parchment for loading the loaves into the oven: when the dough is done, we're going to take it off the parchment, stretch it to 45cm, after which we can put the loaves back on the unfolded parchment lengthwise. Very handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And extremely important: do NOT use wax paper. Yes, it's non-stick, but it also catches fire in a hot oven. Because it's coated in wax/parrafin. The stuff generic candles are made of. And yes, I did make that mistake once, a long time ago. Once is all you need)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small sidenote here for the American audience: you might be familiar with the "&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Perforated-Aluminum-French-Baguette-Bread/dp/B0015QPYQ8"&gt;baguette mold&lt;/a&gt;", and as handy as they sound, they have no place, whatsoever, at all, in the traditional baguette baking process. Traditional baguette are hearth baked, and that means the loaves sit directly on the stone. The most traditional way to do things here is to use a couche for proofing the dough, and then transferring them directly onto the hearth deck for baking. However, in the interest of practicality, using parchment for both steps is the least offensive (as in "it is an offense to do this") alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, your loaves may not all be the same length. As long as the difference is about an inch, don't worry about it. The important part is that the dough will proof in roughly the right shape, after which we're going to reshape the loaves, so a little variation in size at this point is going to be completely undone by the time we get ready for baking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="proofing-to-dough-roughly-2h-"&gt;Proofing to dough: (roughly 2h)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-15.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many, many, &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; ways to proof dough, but I like precision, so I spent some money to get that: this is a generic roasting pan that also happens to work really well as a proofing pan, sitting on top of a heat mat intended for seeding vegetables and potting plants (&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hydrofarm-MT10008--20-Inch-Seedling-Heat/dp/B000E3DDP2"&gt;$40 for a 20"x20" mat&lt;/a&gt;), hooked up to a &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hydrofarm-MTPRTC-Digital-Thermostat-Heat/dp/B000NZZG3S"&gt;simple thermostat&lt;/a&gt; ($30). This mat can't really get all that hot, but the temperature range it produces is specific to germinating seeds, and the temperatures that are good for germinating seeds are exactly the same temperatures that are good for germinating yeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cheaper option is to proof your bread in your oven with the oven light on (provided it's incandescent and not LED) because that creates an above-room-temperature environment without getting overly hot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically: go with what works - my solution lets me say "proof at 35C" and then walk away for a while without needing to check whether it's doing what I'm hoping it's doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-16.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's enjoy the magic of time: on the left are the loaves that we got after rolling them into fat sauasages, before we start proofing. The middle shows the loaves after an hour (at which point we probably need to turn on the oven) and after another 45 minutes, we get the fat doughsplosions on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-17.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're wonding why we need to turn on the oven 45 minutes before we actually start baking: we're actually turning it on about an hour before we start baking. Because it's going to take a long time to heat up properly: we're going to hearthbake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a fancy word for "baking using stones". And I recommend getting a pizza stone because never buy something that can only be used for one thing. A pizza stone is super handy to have for many reasons, one of which is that it lets us bake proper baguettes (another obvious use is baking delicious thin crust pizze).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one in this picture is a &lt;a href="http://www.pizzacraft.com"&gt;Pizzacraft&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005IF2YOW"&gt;20"x13.5"x1" stone&lt;/a&gt; ($30 when on sale), and that much stone takes a while to heat to 260C (500F). That's right: we're baking these breads in a very hot oven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, because your oven will lie to you about how hot it is, put a $5 oven thermometer on the stone so it can register the temperature just above the stone, instead. Your oven may say it's done heating up to 260C, but the stone might still only be 190C. If we were to bake at those temperatures, the bread will die a very sad death in the oven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="final-shaping-10m-"&gt;Final shaping (10m)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-18.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After our 1 hour 45 of proofing, now comes the tricky part: getting the dough off the parchment. You could have, in theory, sprayed the parchment with some oil so that the dough doesn't get stuck at all, but again: we're making traditional French bread, not &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Focaccia"&gt;focaccia&lt;/a&gt; or pizza dough, and oil is not part of the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My approach is to simply dust the loaves with flour after taking them out of the proofing box and then, using a flat scraper, starting from the sides, use short "scrapes" to get the scraper to underneath the loaf from the side, lift it up a little, and pull the scraper back. Gently repeat this up and down the loaf and it'll detach from the paper fairly quickly. Once losse, we can roll them off onto our work surface by simply lifting the paper between loaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-18b.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above picture, you can see the parchment showing signs of scaping to the right, along the sides of the first loaf, with the second image showing the same process for the second loaf, after the first fully separated and got "rolled" off the parchement, resting upside down on the work surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-19.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, we do this four times... and while doing this, you'll notice that the dough is now &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; supple and elastic, which is good: that's exactly what we need, because it'll make the dough "spring" in the oven beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-20.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make the album-poster-bread up top, we now "fold" each loaf, by taking the sides, gently pulling them towards each other over the center, and pinching them so they stick together. This makes the loaves a little less wide, but will make them look rather pretty: after pinch-folding, flip them over back onto the parchment, making sure they stretch the length of the parchment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may get some pretty damn big bubbles while doing this, and if you're worried about those: it's perfectly okay to pop them. The middle image shows the loaf after it's been pinch-folded along the bottom, with bubbles developing, and on the right, post-surgery where I popped the obvious ones back into place with a sharp knife point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BUT: what if we skip this step? What if we just bake the soft and springy dough without pinch-folding it up on itself? Well... let's just say the result is bread, but it's bread with issues. After we finish up with the procedure for the bread up top, we'll look at what happens if we don't pinch-fold the dough. Be warned though: the result is pretty bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-21.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Placing the dough back on the parchment can seem tricky: because the dough's super elastic by now, they might stretch "too far", being too long for the parchment, but don't worry!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dough's super-tolerant right now (unlike when we were rolling it earlier, before proofing) so we can simply "force" it to a roughly straight, parchment-fitting length, and give it a minute or two to rest. The dough's elastic nature will make it pull itself back together, to the point where most wrinkles will be virtually straight surface again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also want to make sure our loaves don't dry out, so use a spray bottle (with water) and mist the loaves a little so they don't dry out too much: it may be a high-hydration dough, but any drying we can prevent, is drying we should prevent. Once we've done all loaves, give them another mist and let them rest for a few minutes so they can all recover. And then once they no longer look super wrinkly we can move on to baking our bread!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also a fun fact: we're not really making true baguette, which is typically 65cm long and must weight 250 grams, but we're also not making its thinner cousin, the ficelle, which is about 32cm long and must weigh 100 grams. We're making something in between, longer and wider than a ficelle, more narrow than a baguette, but also a little heavier than a baguette.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we were running a boulangerie in France, we would not be able to sell what we're making here as baguette, ficelle, or even as flûte. We'd have to come up with a new name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-22.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before loading the loaves in the oven, they need "scoring", in which we tactically cut into the dough so that when it goes into the oven it can expand in a controlled fashion, rather than by breaking through the crust haphazardly as it's forming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dust the tops with flour, and then with a very sharp knife, cut across the bread as per the image on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me emphasize that: use a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; sharp knife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or use a &lt;a href="http://www.kingarthurflour.com/shop/items/lame-bread-slashing-tool"&gt;lame&lt;/a&gt; (roughly pronounced "lah-may", because it's French) which is a handle onto which you fit a disposable razor blade. However, I don't use single-use tools, and I don't shave with disposable blades, so I don't own a lame. I use a super sharp knife instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: it's easy to cut "too deep", but the dough's also very relaxed atm, so if you just cut across the surface without any real pressure behind the cut, you should get decent scoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we make a mistake, we want to much rather cut too shallow than too deep. Why? If we score too deep, the bread will basically "deflate" before we can bake it, and it'll never rise. It'll come out terrible and will pretty much only be usable for bread pudding, if that. However, if we cut too shallow, the bread will find the weakest parts of the crust and literally burst at those seams as the heat of the oven forces it to expand. This will look gnarly, but is infinitely better than scoring too deep, because the bread itself is probably still going to be edible, and is quite likely even tasty. It'll just look really weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-23.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember when I said to use a sharp knife? This is my solution: a $10 "speedy sharp" carbide sharpener and a 5" utility knife, both last considerably longer than disposable razors on a plastic handle. And no, you should not use a carbide sharpener as a regular sharpener, because it'll wreck your knives, but to maximise an edge with two or three strokes on an otherwise already sharpened knife, it's perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before scoring, I give the utility knife a quick sharpening, after which it'll slice through dough, even a wet dough like this one, like it's not even there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="baking-20m-25m-"&gt;Baking (20m-25m)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-24.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we can bake! Open the oven, remove the thermometer (yes, that's speaking from experience), load the breads onto the stone, and close the oven back up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let the bread bake at 260C this way for 5 minutes. It needs a few minutes to "spring" into a shape that will let us pummel it with French baking tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-25.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is "sprung" dough: after those 5 minutes, no real baking has happened yet (despite the fact that it's been subjected to a constant 260C worth of heat), but the dough got hot enough, fast enough, for the gas trapped inside the dough to expand while the dough around it started hardening fast enough to trap the gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a look at those score lines: whereas initially they were only separated a few millimeters before loading, after those 5 minutes of spring, they're massive! In fact, we're seeing that we could have probably cut a little deeper: the bread tried to expand more than the scores allowed for, and they "bubbled" a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes the fun part: steam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-26.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steam is essential for proper crust development. Professional ovens have steam injection; we have a cup of water, instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A warning up front: water is dangerous around hot glass. It can crack it, it can explode it, it's not a safe combination, so remember that in the following step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the initial 5 minutes of spring time, open the oven door, quickly throw half a cup of water against the left side of the oven, and half a cup against the right side of the oven, and close the door again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a near instant blast of steam and we'll be leaving the bread to steam-bake for 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for the additional disclaimers: obviously, don't throw the water on glass. If you have a glass-covered light in your oven, don't throw the water directly on that. Having the steam hit it is fine, just don't hit the glass itself with the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, if you've never done this before, you might micro-damage your oven, because we're going to be shocking the inner walls and that might lead to interesting things like enamel powder getting released during the shocking. You don't want that on your bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done this to my ovens often enough to not even give it a second thought (and I'll break in a new oven by running it through this procedure a few times until I'm sure there's no material ejection due to shocking), but if you're not, another option is to have a metal pan at the base of the oven, and pouring the water in that, rather than throwing it against the walls. It'll probably warp the pan, so make sure it's cheap and not a pan you actually care about, but your oven will stay pristine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-27.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After steam baking for five minutes, we open the door to let out the steam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAND BEHIND, NOT OVER, THE DOOR WHEN YOU DO THIS: STEAM IS HOT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, I know, you're thinking "yeah but it's only 100C, because water boils at 100C" and that is not how steam works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science time: liquid H₂O ("water") is liquid because of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydrogen_bond"&gt;hydrogen bonds&lt;/a&gt;, which break down at 100C (at 1 atmosphere pressure), turning the water into steam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once evaporated into steam, the now completely free H₂O molecules can reach arbitrary temperatures. In fact, they'll comfortably reach 3000C (5430F) before steam breaks down into &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plasma_%28physics%29"&gt;plasma&lt;/a&gt;, so: steam in an oven set to any temperature above 100C will simply be as hot as the oven can make it. In this case, we're baking at about 260C, so by opening the oven door, you're releasing an invisible cloud of &lt;em&gt;incredibly hot&lt;/em&gt; steam, and you don't want to stand in the cloud when you release it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While, on the upside, it'll cool down in less than a second, you still don't want to be the first thing the steam hits: all that energy has to go somewhere, and you don't want to be the thing that receives it. If you are: you'll heal, don't worry about that part, but you'll have a bad time until then (and yes, that's again speaking from experience).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the steam's been let out, close the oven door, turn the temperature down to 230C (445F) and leave the bread to bake for 10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also the point where I typically remove the parchment paper, because from here on out things are going to be hotter than parchment paper can deal with, and the bread's set enough to slide off the parchment without deforming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-28.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your oven seems to bake a little uneven, reorder the bread after 5 minutes. Mine bakes a little hot at the back, so I reorder the loaves such that they're reordered to least-baked-looking at the back (with the least baked side facing the back), most-baked-looking at the front (with the most baked side facing the door).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-29.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the 10 minutes of regular baking, the result is this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That looks pretty good! But this isn't a true hearth oven, and I find that the sides of my bread don't build up as well as in a true hearth oven (with heating coming from all directions, rather than just from below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, there's a really simple way to deal with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-30.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn off the oven, flip the bread over, and pop it back into the oven. The pizza stone will still be hot enough, but the ambient temperature will plummet, letting us send heat specifically up into the top and sides of the bread. I tend to do this for five minutes because it just yields a nicer bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="after-baking-30m-minimum-"&gt;After baking (30m minimum)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-31.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once baked, the bread is not done. Science teaches us that at this point, the dough inside the bread is technically gelatinised. It absolutely, positively, NEEDS to cool down before we can eat this bread, tempting as the bread smells. If you were to cut into it right now, it'd taste bad, and feel rubbery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: cool the bread on a wire rack, and give it at least half an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, this is when we get our first indication of whether we succeeded: we can listen for crackle! (aside from actually eating the bread, this is my favourite part of baking traditional French bread!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the crust will contract as it cools, and because it has nowhere to go, the resulting contractions will actually (micro) fracture the crust, and every fracture comes with an audible crackle. A good crust will audibly crackle (lots!) while it's cooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we don't hear crackling, we should be worried: we may have baked at too low a temperature, or we may not have used enough steam, or we may not have radiated the top enough at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-32.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick look at the result of our scoring: that's some mighty fine expansion we got there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-33.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let's look at the "crumb", which is bread jargon for the texture of the inside of the bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the bread's cooled at least half an hour, we slice it up to see what it looks like on the inside, and we slice it parallel to the scores, because that gives us nice long slices of bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember: just because the bread itself isn't wide, doesn't mean we can't get nice long slices from a loaf!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the last thing we want is the kind of "dense, white bread texture" that you find in many a restaurant. If we see that, then the dough didn't develop properly or we worked it too much, compacting it and releasing too much gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, we want a good mix of fine, medium, and the occasional large hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-34.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will do! Now, finally, we can put some toppings on that and pig out on freshly baked traditional French bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you want to go over all these steps in a more structured, textual form, you can find those over at &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/pomax/19938891750"&gt;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pomax/19938891750&lt;/a&gt;, which lends itself better to the "single picture and a wall of text" format, but of course without all photos that follow the process of making traditional French bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-if-we-don-t-want-to-eat-all-the-bread-right-away-"&gt;What if we don't want to eat all the bread right away?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-35.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you might be thinking "But wait, I don't have anywhere to keep these fresh..." but you might be wrong!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to its crustiness, this kind of bread will keep perfectly fine for a day or two simply loosely wrapped in paper. See that picture? That's brown shipping paper that you get for free from Amazon because they use yards and yards of that stuff as packing padding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason paper is so great is that it doesn't trap moisture like plastic or a sealed container, so the crust doesn't getting soggy (on on hot summer days, mold!), but it also doesn't release moisture so fast the bread completely dries out, it takes it a day or two, which is exactly long enough to eat all that bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the bread will lose some of its distinct crunchiness the next day, but we can bring that right back with this guy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/bread-36.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The humble spray bottle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a loaf of next-day-bread, hold it up by its tip and spray the entire loaf, front, back, sides, up and down, then pop it in the oven, set it to 180C, and have it warm back up for 5 to 10 minutes. This crisps the crust right back up, and gives you nice warm bread to munch on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't have a spray bottle? They're dirt cheap, but we can be cheaper and just use our kitchen sink: turn on the tap , and quickly run the whole length of the bread underneath it one way, flip, and run back the other way. Obviously the "quickly" is key here, we don't want to soak the bread, but we do want the entire crust wet. Then we pop it into the oven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science time: what happens is that the water soaks into the top layer of the bread, doing two things: acting as a heat shield for the inside of the bread (since the water has to evaporate off before more intense heat makes it into the bread past the crust) and acting as a smoothing agent for the cracked crust, effectively rebuilding it by turning it into something that is almost like a dough again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 10 minutes at 180C, the water will have evaporated off and the crust will have hardened back up, while the inside of the bread got just warm enough to be lovely, but not piping hot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to traditional French bread, second day bread can be just as good as fresh bread! (although that said, most people in France will just throw the bread out. Or use it as an ingredient for a dish that requires day-old bread, like bread pudding, or crostini)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="so-what-if-we-hadn-t-pinch-folded-the-dough-"&gt;So, what if we hadn't pinch-folded the dough?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/unshaped-01.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember when we asked "but what happens if we don't pinch-fold the dough?"... let's examine that idea, because things would have turned out a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one, 69.5% hydration is too high for an unfolded loaf, and the dough doesn't really know where to spring to. The scores settle too quickly, so the loaves don't look very nice, and the large holes that formed during proofing stay pretty damn large. We had to poke a few holes during pinch-folding, and it was a good thing we did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/unshaped-04.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big holes in the dough mean even bigger pockets of hot air at the surface of the bread as it bakes, which means that there isn't anything to act as a heat bufffer for the crust over an air pocket, and so the bread will bake very uneven: where there's dough, things'll generally be fine, but if there's a bubble, that section will bake much faster than the rest of the bread, leading to charred sections on an otherwise potentially decent bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See if you can count the number of air pockets in just this section of one of the breads baked without pinch-folding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/unshaped-02.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 500px" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, those huge pockets of air also make it much harder to use the bread "as bread". It might work well with a bowl of olive oil, but that's about it: the holes are just too big to make the bread of any practical use beyond "dipping bread".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is particularly obvious in the next close up picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/gh-weblog-2/images/baguette/unshaped-03.jpg" style="max-height:500px; max-width: 100%" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, this isn't so much "bread" anymore as "slices of bready colander". Toppings are literally just going to fall through our slices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: pinch-folding. It's a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="and-that-s-it-go-make-some-bread-"&gt;And that's it: go make some bread!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you have any questions of comments, hit that comment &lt;a href="http://github.com/pomax/pomax.github.io/issues"&gt;link in the lower left&lt;/a&gt;, or tweet at me &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/therealpomax"&gt;@TheRealPomax&lt;/a&gt; and I'll be happy to engage with your on the finer points of breadification.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Baking</category>
<category>French Bread</category>
<category>Baguette</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1438891326649</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1438891326649</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 20:02:06 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> A Love letter to Flickr</title>
<description>&lt;h2 id="-dear-flickr"&gt;“Dear Flickr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/Pomax"&gt;We go back a few years, don't we&lt;/a&gt;. We started hanging out in 2006, and officially hooked up in May of 2007, and have been together since. I've not always spent as much time with you as I would have liked, but the relationship was steady, and when I took photographs, you showed them to the world, in the hopes that others would enjoy them as much as we did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Over the years, you started to take the helm more and more, deciding what we could show our visitors, taking way the short descriptions I worked so hard on to make sure visitors understood what they were looking at, turning my gallery into a "wallpaper" because some of your friends saw other people do that and it looked cool, adding ways to display my photographs for me that I didn't appreciate, and most recently, claiming that people prefer to view my works as if they were looking through my portfolio as a "camera roll".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think you need to come back to me and sit down for a bit, so we can talk about this. You've started running this Photography exhibit on your own, without so much as even asking me, or letting me say "no, this is not how I want people to experience our shared efforts, they are bad", just steamrolling ahead like you know what's best for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-you-used-to-be-about-showing-the-world-photographs"&gt;“You used to be about showing the world photographs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Remember when you loved photography? You were enthusiastic about tons of people having photos they wanted to show the world, with as much detail as possible, curated the way they thought the photos worked best, with a default exhibit space that allowed people to browse the walls, walk up to photos that looked interesting, and read the descriptions, even letting them walk over to the more detailed floor guide for each work to get all the additional information that we, the curators, thought would be pertinent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Those were happy times. You ran the art gallery, I had the art, and people could come in and immediately enjoy what we, together, had to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But then you shut down the art gallery, and started a hip, new, place. One I did not understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-i-just-wanted-the-world-to-enjoy-my-work"&gt;“I just wanted the world to enjoy my work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Your hip new place took the works I had made, and instead of hanging them on the wall, easy to walk past, with titles and descriptions that people could read and feel good about, you decided to just tile a single wall with every photo I ever took. I don't know how you did it, but the wall ran on forever. Every photograph we ever exhibited was on it, but none of them said what they were of, or gave any details about why it was taken, or worth looking at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I confess, I didn't understand why you did it. I hated it. What use is a wall that is so long that people can't even get to the end? Is there even an end? I never got to it - much like everyone else, after walking for 5 minutes I was so overstimulated with just contextless, meaningless "pictures" that I left my own exhibit and went across town to galleries like &lt;a href="http://imgur.com"&gt;Imgur&lt;/a&gt;, and if I felt particularly depressed, &lt;a href="http://fukung.net"&gt;Fukung&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You made me unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-you-did-realise-you-were-hurting-our-relationship-i-think-"&gt;“You did realise you were hurting our relationship, I think...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I stuck with you, but I wasn't happy. You were doing things that I saw didn't just hurt me, but were hurting everyone around us. All our friends who you represented felt the same. Some of them initially liked the hip new look, but many of them just didn't understand it. How did this help people enjoy our work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So you backed off a little. You spaced out the artworks a bit, so people wouldn't experience sensory overload so much, but you still left off the descriptions, saying people would reach for the exhibit guide if they wanted more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But that's not how exhibits work, and user visits for individual works plummeted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think you noticed that, too. I had hoped you would do the sensible thing, but I think you took it the wrong way and started doing things that felt, to me, like desperation. Instead of focussing on better exhibit organisation, and playbooks for how to set up specific kinds of exhibits, you decided to move our gallery to the conference center you just bought, and open it up to everyone, for free, with unlimited gallery space for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When I asked you how you were paying for all of this, you smiled and said "we're getting sponsored by some big name companies, and we'll be hanging their product posters in between photographs". I can't believe you said that, it's like I was talking to someone who didn't care about photography anymore, or even exhibiting good collections of art works. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This was someone who had lost interest and was finding pleasures in figuring out new and creative ways to make numbers go up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You even tried to cancel our exhibition contract, saying that because you now allowed everyone, of course that included me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-and-you-became-a-bit-anti-social-too-"&gt;“And you became a bit anti-social, too.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Remember how we could see what friends were exhibiting in your other galleries? You changed that so that it wasn't even possible to see what a single friend was doing. Where we used to be able to see that seven friends had updated their exhibition space, now we needed to scroll through a long, unorganized list of updates. It became impossible to keep tabs on what other people were doing in the photograph space we once ran together. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What's the point of recommending following "people I might know", for instance, (I think you liked Twitter, you clearly just repeated what they were doing, but they had a reason for it, and you, I think, didn't) if I then cannot see what these people have been doing? It was confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You were confusing me, Flickr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-it-s-true-i-tried-going-it-alone-for-a-bit"&gt;“It's true: I tried going it alone for a bit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You were driving me away, to the point where I was looking for ways to get my artwork back from you, in a way that would let me exhibit it the way we used to do. Letting people walk around the space, and lean over to read a description here and there, grabbing the exhibit guide when they really wanted, and letting them get as close to the works as they wanted. Remember that blank wall we used to have where people could take individual photographs and hang them up, on their own? I wanted to add that back in, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I couldn't find any art galleries that would do what you used to do. So I rented a space, and &lt;a href="http://flickr.nihongoresources.com/Pomax"&gt;started my own&lt;/a&gt;. I wrote a playbook on how to &lt;a href="https://github.com/Pomax/flickrmirror"&gt;set up a gallery in our old style&lt;/a&gt;, and for a while I was happy. I could tell people to just visit my gallery while you did you own thing at your corporate conference center and I could ignore you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I even came up with some ideas that worked for me, like a film strip while navigating, and I sent you text messages telling you what I'd done and that I didn't like what you were doing right now, but felt it would benefit everyone if you copied those ideas. I think you acted on some of those texts, although of course not on all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ultimately, of course, I couldn't drive enough people to my own little art gallery. They all knew about your conference center, and while I had a small clique of friends who knew where my exhibits "really" ran, it was too much effort to keep up with multiple exhibitions across town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-it-feels-like-you-re-coming-back-though"&gt;“It feels like you're coming back, though&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I've not been the nicest to you, I know. We drifted apart, but it feels like you realised that. Or, at least, understand that what you've been doing has perhaps been more about "just making numbers go up" than about "getting the world to love the exhibits you run", and you've started to change your ways a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I very recently posted a short notice in a local paper about how I would love it if you brought back personal contracts, so that we could track exhibit numbers together, and the next day you announced that was coming back. I was overjoyed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There's a ways to go yet, but it feels like we're at a point in this relationship where I can either walk away, or I can confess all these frustrations I've had over the last seven years, and hope that some of them make sense to you, even if they make you angry because I'm pointing them out. I think you deserve to be angry at me, as long as we can work together to channel that anger, and bring back the joy of exhibiting photographs to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There's some odd things I don't understand, that maybe you can explain, or maybe you can look at and go "yeah, these things don't make much sense, I was just trying out things to see whether any of it would stick". The Camera Roll, for instance, serves no purpose that I can tell. Maybe you have a plan for it, but it feels like something you should take back out until you know what that is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You're still just showing photographs on the walls, instead of putting up the little description plaques next to them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It's still very hard for people to see the full size photographs, too. Instead of letting people walk up close to each work, you did something clever with lenses, and instead when people try to walk closer, you keep them where they are and just zoom in on the reduced work. I... don't think that's a nice thing to do to people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sure, you added "lots of interactions" for people, but you haven't labeled any of them. They're just hieroglyphs that people need to guess at, and there are so many of them that it feels like you're, at least at this point in your life, preferring option overload over just letting people experience the works at their own pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But you're also improved some things, and that's the part that I think matters most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-let-s-talk-"&gt;“Let's talk?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I'm writing you this letter because I don't know how to talk to you right now. I tried calling a few times, but it goes to an answering machine that tells me to come to the conference center and leave my issues with the info desk. That's not fair, I think. Of course, you need an info desk for regular questions, or reports of where your exhibits got damaged, or a door got stuck, stuff like that, but the info desk is not a place where you and I can talk about the fundamental changes that I think are hurting not just you and I, but also this town we live in. It used to be full of art galleries, and you've slowly turned it into a wallpaper farm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That wasn't nice, and I'm sorry for having said that, but that's where we are. Can we talk?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-i-still-love-you-but-it-s-hard"&gt;“I still love you, but it's hard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don't know what to do, hopefully you still want to be friends, and we can talk this through, but I have no powerful punchline to end this letter with. We both want, I think, to show the world great art, but the way you've been doing it the last few years and allowed other towns to do it better, and rather than learning from that, you've just been adding more and more things that drive more and more people away. I want to help you fix that. I want to bring back spontaneous, discoverable, enjoyable exhibits to our town. Without destroying everything you built up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-with-more-love-than-my-friends-tell-me-you-deserve-"&gt;“With more love than my friends tell me you deserve,&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Pomax”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Flickr</category>
<category>Photography</category>
<category>Love letter</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1438539341719</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1438539341719</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 18:15:41 GMT</pubDate>
</item></channel>
</rss>
