<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<atom:link href="http://pomax.github.io/gh-weblog-2/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<title>Pomax.github.io</title>
<description>My blog on github</description>
<link>http://pomax.github.io</link>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 23:26:25 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 23:26:25 GMT</pubDate>
<ttl>1440</ttl>
<item>
<title>Creating VST/AU/etc audio plugins in 2017</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Probably the best tutorial on getting started writing a VST plugins (whether you want to make an instrument or a filter) is Martin Finke's &lt;a href="http://www.martin-finke.de/blog/tags/making_audio_plugins.html"&gt;Making Audio Plugins&lt;/a&gt;. It covers going from "zero to hero" but it has one downside: it's from 2012, and the tools used have some issues in 2017. Not big issues, just "big enough to frustrate people who would otherwise dive right in, into doing something else instead". So, what can we do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, it's 2017 (coming up to 2018) and I'm going to assume you're using Windows mostly because that's what I do (because several audio production tools I use only exist for Windows. I also have a mac, yes I own Ableton, no I'm not covering using XCode in 2017 here. But if you want to do that work for me, I will be more than happy to add your findings to this blog post! (hit me up &lt;a href="https://github.com/pomax/pomax.github.io/issues"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to discuss that!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="getting-the-right-tools"&gt;Getting the right tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's 2017, you're probably on Windows 10, so let's go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grab &lt;a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/downloads/"&gt;Visual Studio 2017 Community Edition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you install that, make sure to check all the SDKs and install those. Pretty important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="following-the-instructions"&gt;Following the instructions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While "Making Audio Plugins &lt;a href="http://www.martin-finke.de/blog/articles/audio-plugins-002-setting-up-wdl-ol/"&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;" covers most of it, once you've used python to create your first plugin code, and you're loading the &lt;code&gt;.sln&lt;/code&gt; in Visual C++, you're going to hit warnings and errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don't worry, it's okay&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accept the suggestion by VC++ to upgrade the project to the modern SDKs (which it will fail at, but again, that's okay), and then instead of trying to compile &lt;code&gt;MyFirstPlugin-app&lt;/code&gt;, first make sure the project and Visual C++ know that we're working on Windows 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="update-the-platform"&gt;Update the platform&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;code&gt;Project&lt;/code&gt; and then &lt;code&gt;Properties&lt;/code&gt;, and in the "General" tab, change the platform tools from Windows XP (yep. Windows XP) to Windows 10. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't do this, you'll see errors about SDK_71A things not being set in the registry. They are complete red herrings, because what they really mean is "the project is using an SDK that I don't know about", which is true: we're on Windows 10, we're using SDK version 141, not version 71!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="update-your-include-path"&gt;Update your include path&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still in &lt;code&gt;Project&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;Properties&lt;/code&gt;, in the "VC++ Directories" section, add two directories to the "Includes" path. Specifically, you want to add the &lt;code&gt;mu&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;shared&lt;/code&gt; dirs for the Windows 10 SDK that you're working with. As of today, for the Fall creator edition, that would be &lt;code&gt;C:\Program Files (x86)\Windows Kits\10\Include\10.0.16299.0&lt;/code&gt; so you need to add the following to that path:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;C:\Program Files (x86)\Windows Kits\10\Include\10.0.16299.0\mu;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;C:\Program Files (x86)\Windows Kits\10\Include\10.0.16299.0\shared;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't do this, or use the wrong path, you'll probably see a lot of errors about a missing &lt;code&gt;windows.h&lt;/code&gt; (which is in the &lt;code&gt;mu&lt;/code&gt; directory) and/or a missing &lt;code&gt;winapifamily.h&lt;/code&gt; (which is in the &lt;code&gt;shared&lt;/code&gt; directory).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="retargeting-the-project"&gt;Retargeting the project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, after accepting these changes to the project properties, we right-click on &lt;code&gt;MyFirstPlugin-app&lt;/code&gt; and choose "retarget projects". This will pop up a dialog that lets you pick the SDK version, and make sure to pick the &lt;code&gt;10.0.....&lt;/code&gt; version that matches what we used for the Platform Tools in the project properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="you-re-good-to-go-"&gt;You're good to go!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, now we can get back to that awesome tutorial and make some audio plugins. Select &lt;code&gt;MyFirstPlugin-app&lt;/code&gt;, hit F5 to start a compile, and "things should just work(tm)".&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Audio</category>
<category>VST</category>
<category>Programming</category>
<category>VC++</category>
<category>2017</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1512169175433</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1512169175433</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 22:59:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>A beer riddle</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Cold beer I promise, if but in name; pour me one for the difference to remain. Lakes of beer I pass in strain - what am I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background: black; color: black"&gt;
My name spells cold yet warm I work, my job to offer beer a fork: swim along or cloud the flow. It is my job to tell it: "no". What am I?
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background: black; color: black"&gt;
Once in water, I now swim here, holding that which muddles beer. Separate it from what is dear, thrown away once beer is clear. What am I?
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the answer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background: black; color: black"&gt;
From fish we get a jellied web, that filters the last bits of drab, from finished beers sent off for casking: "&lt;a style="color: black" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isinglass"&gt;isinglass&lt;/a&gt;" the name of asking.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>

<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1490481349209</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1490481349209</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2017 22:35:49 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> Localization is hard.</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I know, that seems like an obvious statement, but I want to dig a little deeper because just because you have a "web thing" that people might want to see translated or even fully localized, that doesn't mean that they can, or even if they can, that it's easy for them to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, this is a story of a project that was blessed with two independent users wanting to translate content to Chinese and Japanese, and a code base that was &lt;em&gt;absolutely not ready for that&lt;/em&gt;. As of this blog post, it most definitely is, and that's been a few weeks worth of journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me take you through the travel log.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="once-upon-a-time-there-was-a-primer-on-b-zier-curves-https-pomax-github-io-bezierinfo-"&gt;Once upon a time there was a &lt;a href="https://pomax.github.io/bezierinfo"&gt;Primer on Bézier curves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or rather, there was a &lt;a href="http://processingjs.org"&gt;Processing.js&lt;/a&gt; based exploration of the basics of Bézier curves because I was working on font generation and wanted to understand the intricacies of Bézier curves for the purposes of drawing curve outlines. There weren't any really good resources on the topic, and because the best way to learn something is to teach it, I figured I'd write my own explanation, put it online, and learn how they worked that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I learned more and more I kept updating that one short page until it had became a rather long page, and once it started to show up fairly high in Google results for "bezier curves" (typos included because who has the time to write "é" when you're not on a French keyboard) I started taking "making sure it was sort of usable" more seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jumping from 2011 to 2017, the page underwent a fair number of changes, and I thought I had a pretty good setup until a few weeks ago:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Primer itself is a &lt;a href="https://facebook.github.io/react"&gt;React&lt;/a&gt;-managed single page... err... page. It's just a page, not an app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each section is a &lt;a href="https://github.com/Pomax/BezierInfo-2/tree/4c3be7105161d69774e622432654a5dbc62bae96/components/sections"&gt;separate JSX file&lt;/a&gt; wrapping both the JS functionality and the web content, with the &lt;code&gt;render()&lt;/code&gt; function simply housing a big block of almost-HTML code with virtually no templating, so it reads like normal webpages (for the most part).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the article as a whole loads all the sections, &lt;a href="https://github.com/Pomax/BezierInfo-2/blob/4c3be7105161d69774e622432654a5dbc62bae96/components/Navigation.jsx"&gt;mines them for title data, uses that to build a ToC&lt;/a&gt;, and then just renders the entire article.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also has clever code for dealing with "I just want to write about maths, not program about maths", so sections can contain code that isn't legal JSX in the slightest, but that's okay: babel loaders do some preprocessing and when the code actually gets to the "convert react to plain JS" step, everything is perfectly fine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bundling uses &lt;a href="https://webpack.github.io"&gt;Webpack&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href="http://babeljs.io/"&gt;babel&lt;/a&gt; for converting JSX and ES6+ code to plain old ES5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a number of custom webpack loaders are used to turn "my code" into "actually spec-compliant JSX" (insofar as there is a spec, of course):&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href="https://github.com/Pomax/BezierInfo-2/blob/4c3be7105161d69774e622432654a5dbc62bae96/lib/p-loader.js"&gt;&lt;code&gt;p-loader&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which replaces &lt;code&gt;{&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt; inside paragraphs with JSX-safified versions instead, because to JSX those are templating instructions.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href="https://github.com/Pomax/BezierInfo-2/blob/4c3be7105161d69774e622432654a5dbc62bae96/lib/pre-loader.js"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pre-loader&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which replaces "html sensitive" characters in &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;pre&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; blocks with safe equivalents, so that I can write &lt;code&gt;i &amp;lt; 0&lt;/code&gt; rather than having to bother with remembering to use &lt;code&gt;i &amp;amp;lt; 0&lt;/code&gt;. Which is good: having to remember HTML entities is dumb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href="https://github.com/Pomax/BezierInfo-2/blob/4c3be7105161d69774e622432654a5dbc62bae96/lib/latex-loader.js"&gt;&lt;code&gt;latex-loader&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which does some "genuinely cool shit™"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;SectionHeader&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; component that ensure that each section ends up providing its own fragment identifier for easy &lt;code&gt;index.html#somesection&lt;/code&gt; navigation and bookmarking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly the LaTeX loader is a thing I really like: &lt;a href="http://pomax.github.io/1451617530567/react-with-latex-without-needing-client-side-mathjax"&gt;I wrote about this before&lt;/a&gt;, but for the longest time the on-page LaTeX would simply be parsed client-side using &lt;a href="https://mathjax.org"&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt; but that made the article load really slowly because I use a lot of maths. Like... &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt;. People had to basically wait for 150+ blocks of LaTeX to be typeset by their browser, slowing down the page load, making the page unresponsive, and basically just being super annoying. Worth it for what you got in return, but still annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, eventually, I wrote the latex-loader whose specialized role was to ingest a JSX file, extract all LaTeX code blocks, convert them &lt;em&gt;offline during the build&lt;/em&gt; by running them through MathJax (using &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/mathjax-node"&gt;mathjax-node&lt;/a&gt;), saving the resulting SVG to file, and then generating a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; JSX file in which each LaTeX block got replaced with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img src="latexfile.svg" width="..." height="..."/&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to effect two things: first, excellent load experience for users because their browser wasn't locking up anymore, and second, the page content wouldn't move around anymore because while client-side MathJax means there was no way to tell how much vertical space a conversion result would take up, having actual SVG files means you can just quickly check what their size is going to be and bind an image &lt;code&gt;width&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;height&lt;/code&gt; value so that the DOM already knows how much space it needs even before an image is loaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, it was &lt;em&gt;pretty&lt;/em&gt; sweet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="and-then-contributors-show-up-"&gt;And then contributors show up.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been working on the Primer pretty much on my own since 2011, with some help from people in terms of advice or suggestions, but never in the sense that they took the code, changes something radically, and then filed a PR and discussed the changes to get them landed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February of 2017, that changed. In the span of a week two people contacted me because they wanted to translate the article to their own language. Specifically: Chinese and Japanese. And this is where, if you're an English content creator, things get interesting because that's not just translation: that's localization. While of course translation is involved, things like "how maths statement are organized" also changes, and probably some other things you hadn't even thought of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I really wanted to take these folks up on their offer: getting the Primer translated so that the content is more meaningful for Chinese and Japanese audiences is huge! But my code base was written by one person, for one person, for one language, without any affordances to the possibility of eventual translation. so I did the only thing I could think of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I told them I was super interested in having them help out, but would need a little time to make sure they could work on the code&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where you lose contributors, by the way, but it's still the correct way to deal with people showing up wanting to help doing a thing you had never spent any time thinking of at all: when the world shows up at your doorstep asking to help you, you make it some tea, express your deepest gratitude and then while they're hopwfully distracted by the cookies you work your ass off to make sure it doesn't go "well I should go again". You make it want to stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="code-base-changes-let-s-talk-about-failures-"&gt;Code base changes: let's talk about failures.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've worked with localized code bases before and there are some nice solutions out there for websites and apps. I figured I'd see if &lt;a href="https://www.transifex.com"&gt;Transifex&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://pontoon.mozilla.org"&gt;Mozilla's Pontoon&lt;/a&gt; could be used, because that's what I've used in the past, but this is where traditional localization solutions break down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transifex is a translation service that lets you define your project in terms of key-value mappings, where you use the keys in your own content, and translators can create translations of the associated values to whatever language you want to have supported. You then download your latest translations from transifex and apply the key/value mappings to your content to achieve a translated web page, app, UI, etc. Now, while this works quite really well for web apps, and really well for general UI,  things get tricky for content like articles. In articles, where the content is structured in paragraphs and the ordering matters for the tone of the text, asking localizers to translate paragraphs or even single sentences fully detached from what comes before or after is almost guaranteed to give weird translations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To alleviate that problem, Mozilla's Pontoon project offers a sort of "on-page translation" localization system, where you load the website and pontoon UI at the same time, and translators can "double click and translate" text on the page. While that sounds really nice, it turns out that setting it up for "not mozilla sites" is a little bit tricky: you need to run your own copy of pontoon, and a lot of the code assumes it's running on Mozilla infrastructure. However, once you do get that it work, you still have the problem that transifex has: your localizers might have an easier time, but as an author you're still stuck being unable to write text yourself without then having to convert it to an unreadable "mess" of &lt;code&gt;getText('section1-paragraph1')&lt;/code&gt; in your code, so you have no idea what you wrote. You can try to get abstract keys from values (say, by hashing) but then changing even one letter in a paragraph invalidates every translation, which is typically &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; what you want. A little desync is fine for webcontent. Corrections that trickle through are infinitely preferable to "keeping either all sites on the old content, or breaking all translations for a hopefully short while as translators catch up with changes".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems with the methodology of these translation/localization systems outweight the benefits they brought to my project, as they either didn't work for me as author, or didn't work for the nature of the content, so the traditional solutions for adding localization to a site were out. Not because they're unsuitable as localization solutions, but because for this project, they introduced more problems than they solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="code-base-changes-that-work-markdown-"&gt;Code base changes that work: Markdown.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so after about a week of trying to make localization "easy" with string based localization services, instead I figured I'd roll my own solution because I was keeping people waiting for a week at this point and they had every reason to just go "well this Pomax guy's clearly not interested in getting help, time to look for something else to help out on". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, by the way, your single biggest challenge in Open Source: if you thought it was hard to find contributors, it's ten times harder to make sure &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; respond in a timely fashion and make sure there is something for them to get started on. Don't have anything? Take a paid-time-off or vacation day and &lt;em&gt;make sure there are things for them to start on&lt;/em&gt;. Or lose your contributor. If you leave a contributor hanging for more than a day, your project isn't really worth helping out on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I had to make this work, and the solution to the problem was one that basically comes to us from the traditional translation world: detach the content from the code, and translate the content as full length pieces. This is programming, we can make "integrating disparate pieces of code and content" work in at least seventeen different ways, so it's entirely possible to offer authors and translators alike a base case where "here is the section as natural, flowing text, with embedded LaTeX where necessary and code blocks to illustrate how to program stuff. Just translate that". And so that's what I set out to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I decided on a content format: sections would be an &lt;code&gt;index.js&lt;/code&gt; for the JSX code, and a &lt;code&gt;content.en-GB.md&lt;/code&gt; for my own English content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;content would be pulled back into the JSX by... wait...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you pull markdown content into a JSX file? Unlike &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;jsx&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;json&lt;/code&gt;, markdown content can't just be imported in JavaScript or even in Node.js... It's a problem, but really solving this problem before getting back to my contributors would prevent translations from happening, and so &lt;em&gt;I stepped away from the problem and told them I had something they could work with now&lt;/em&gt;. I had a solution &lt;em&gt;for them&lt;/em&gt;, and that came first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it's nice to solve these things as they pop up, but the most important part is still to make sure contributors can start doing what they wanted to do to help, and once I figured out how to at least split up the JSX into "JSX for the skeleton" and "Markdown for the content", I had a solution that unblocked my contributors so that &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; could now at least get started translating and making progress, even if the system for rebuilding the content wasn't done yet and I wouldn't be able to immediately deploy whatever PR they were going to throw my way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their needs came first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I figured out how to at least split up the content as JSX and Markdown, I sat down and split up the preface and first three sections for the primer, creating a few &lt;code&gt;content.en-GB.md&lt;/code&gt; that set the tone for what the markdown would look like, and then I told the hopefully-still-willing-to-be-contributors that if they were still interested in helping out they could now start on these files. All they had to do was copy it to &lt;code&gt;content.zh-CN.md&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;content.ja-JP.md&lt;/code&gt; and then modify that as best they knew how to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while they were doing that, I'd have some time to implement getting the Markdown loaded back into the JSX files to generate a site that, for visitors, was identical to the monolithic English one.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The take-away here is mostly that perfect solutions aren't necessary: if you're balancing priorities &lt;strong&gt;unblock your contributors before you unblock yourself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reintegrating-sections-based-on-jsx-and-markdown"&gt;Reintegrating sections based on JSX and Markdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the contributors were working on their translations, I got back to work integrating Markdown into the JSX, and after a bit of thinking the solution to how to achieve that integration was remarkably simple: &lt;em&gt;you don't&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, that sounds a bit silly, but it's not silly as you might initially think; I solved this problem using the classic problem solving approach of "if X is hard,find out which Y is easy, and find out how you turn X into Y". This is a general life skill when it comes to problem solving and I honestly don't practice it enough, but I practiced it here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pulling markdown into JSX is hard,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pulling JSX into JSX is trivial,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I should convert markdown strings into JSX strings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty good at programming, and both markdown and JSX are, at their code, just string data in a file. As converting string data into other string data is a pretty easy thing if you know how to program, I wrote a script called &lt;code&gt;make-locales.js&lt;/code&gt; which runs through the &lt;code&gt;./components/sections&lt;/code&gt; directories looking for &lt;code&gt;content.*.md&lt;/code&gt; files, filters the list of locales it finds that way, turning it into a list of unique locales, and then for each locale in that list does something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;for (locale in locales) {
  giantMarkdownCollection = getAllContentFilesBelongingTo(locale)
  sectionAndContentMap = convertMarkdown(giantMarkdownCollection)
  convertedToJS = JSON.stringify(sectionAndContentMap)
  filesystem.write(`./locales/${locale}/content.js`, convertedToJS);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Running this script builds a &lt;code&gt;content.js&lt;/code&gt; file that takes a form that matches the one necessary for any Node script (which JSX files are in my code base) to trivially import with a single &lt;code&gt;require('content')&lt;/code&gt; statement. By further making sure the data inside &lt;code&gt;content.js&lt;/code&gt; is keyed in the same way as the original code base organised sections, I basically had a markdown-to-JSX conversion that the original code base didn't even notice was different. Everything basically worked the same as far as it was concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="further-challenges-i-m-not-using-true-markdown"&gt;Further challenges: I'm not using &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; markdown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, while the &lt;code&gt;get all content&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;stringify&lt;/code&gt; operations are pretty easy, the crucial function to get right was that &lt;code&gt;convertMarkdown&lt;/code&gt; function, to turn the markdown syntax into JSX syntax instead. Thankfully, JSX syntax is basically JavaScript with embedded "HTML that follows XML rules", and converting markdown to HTML is super easy: just pick any of twenty or so libraries to do so, and you're essentially done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked the &lt;code&gt;marked&lt;/code&gt; library to do things for me, but there was one real challenge that needed to be tackled: the content I write is a mix of "mostly normal text", "some LaTeX, sometimes", "some divs with specific classes to mark bits as notes, how-to-code, and figures, sometimes" and some JSX for each interactive graphic... also sometimes. And being a pure markdown converter, except for the "normal text" parts &lt;code&gt;marked&lt;/code&gt; kind of didn't like any of that, so how would one make &lt;code&gt;marked&lt;/code&gt; convert things properly? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same problem solution process: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Converting mixed Markdown content is hard,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;converting just plain markdown is trivial,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only convert plain markdown and leave the other bits alone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crucial observation was that in the build system I already had, things like "LaTeX", "divs with classes for notes and howtos" and "JSX" already worked. So really the only thing that &lt;em&gt;needed&lt;/em&gt; additional work was turning the markdown string sections into html string sections. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easy-peasy: I know how to write tokenizers, lexers and grammar parsers in general so I wrote a simple chained chunker that takes a markdown file, and then runs a super simple "chop it up, if I know how to chop it up" action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;data = a full markdown file,
chunks = empty list to fill with data chunks,
chunkers = a list of latex, div, JSX, and BadMarkDown chunkers.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;define a function to act as recursion point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function performChunking(data, chunks, chunker, moreChunkers) {
  if no chunker:
    if data isn't empty:
      chunks.push({ convert: true, data: data })
    return;

  // otherwise, if there is a chunker:
  chunker(data, chunks, moreChunkers);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;and then finally, you just start blindly running through the data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function chunkLatex(data, chunks, chunkMore) {
  // run through the data looking for LaTeX blocks
  while there is data left to examine:
    if there is no latex left:
      performChunking(data.substring(p), chunks, next, otherChunkers);
      exit the chunkLatex function

    if there is, get the start of the latex block.
    Then, parse the non-LaTeX data prior to it using the rest of the chunkers:
        performChunking(data.substring(...), chunks, next=chunkMore[0], chunkMore=chunkMore[1,...])

    And then capture the LaTeX block itself as a "don't convert" block
    chunks.push({ convert: false, type: "latex", start:..., end:..., data:...});
  }
}

function chunkDiv(data, chunks, chunkMore) {
  Same as above, except for &amp;lt;div&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt; delimiters
}

function chunkJSX(data, chunks, chunkMore) {
  Same as above, except for &amp;lt;Graphic..../&amp;gt; lines
}

...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And so forth. This system ensures that a block that has no latex gets further analysed by the "div" code. Any divs are extracted, any non-div code is handed on to the JSX code, and so on and so on until there is no function left to examine with. At that point, we know it's just plain markdown and we record it as a "convert? yes!" data block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of this process (which actually runs &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; quickly), we end up with an object that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;chunked = [
  {
    start: 0,
    end: 312,
    type: "text"
    convert: true,
    data: "# section title\nThis is regular markdown..."
  },
  {
    start: 313
    end: 417,
    type: "LaTeX",
    convert: false,
    data: "\\[\nB(t) = (1-t)^3 + 3 \cdot (1-t)^2t + ... " 
  },
  ...
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And so we simply run through this through a quick &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; function where any data that is marked as "convert? no!" is left alone, any data that is marked as "convert? yes!" is converted by &lt;code&gt;marked&lt;/code&gt; from markdown to HTML data. Then we simply join all the blocks back up, and we actually have the kind of JSX that the original monolithic English article was already using. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winner!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="one-last-thing-javascript-bindings-still-needs-to-work-"&gt;One last thing: JavaScript bindings still needs to work.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the above procedure works &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; well, it left one problem: sections have interactive graphics, which are tied to individual React components. While components were single JSX files that was not a problem, but by pulling the content out I needed a way to make sure that JSX code like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Graphics setup={this.setup} draw={this.draw}/&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; still had a correct understanding of which JavaScript object was supposed to be used when it made calls for &lt;code&gt;this.something()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to this is actually the simplest, borderline trivial,  a bit silly, but super effective: as each mapped chunk is strictly speaking already valid JSX I just took the string data and wrapped it in more string data that just turned it into a function call, wrapping it in &lt;code&gt;function(handler) { return &amp;lt;section&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; at the start and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/section&amp;gt;; }&lt;/code&gt; at the end, and making sure the JSX chunker replaced any &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; with the word &lt;code&gt;handler&lt;/code&gt; instead. The result: code like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;content = [
  "whatis": function(handler) {
    return &amp;lt;section&amp;gt;
     ...
     &amp;lt;Graphics setup={handler.setup} draw={handler.draw} /&amp;gt;
     ...
    &amp;lt;/section&amp;gt;;
  }
  ...
];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And there you have it. Rather than importing this and then using it directly, a component can now import this and then call the function, passing itself in as the "handler":&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var React = require("react");

var Locale = require("../../../lib/locale");
var locale = new Locale(__dirname);

return React.createClass({
  getDefaultProps() {
    return {
      title: locale.getTitle()
    };
  },
  setup() {
    ...
  }
  draw() {
    ...
  }
  render() {
    return locale.getContent(this);
  }
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sorted: suddenly we have a code base that is super easy to localize. Just change the &lt;code&gt;content.{local}.md&lt;/code&gt; file, and the &lt;code&gt;make-locales.js&lt;/code&gt; script will take care of the rest. In fact, with an &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; task that watches for changes in &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; files so that &lt;code&gt;make-locales.js&lt;/code&gt; gets retriggered, and a webpack task for &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt; files in general, live development didn't even need any changing: it just works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="so-what-about-that-latex-is-maths-notation-universal-"&gt;So what about that LaTeX? Is maths notation universal?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="spoilers-not-if-there-s-english-in-it"&gt;spoilers: not if there's English in it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing about localisation: you need to update &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the content to work for a specific locale. Translating all the English text to something like Chinese is great and all but if the graphics still have English in them, things get weird. And while at this point the contributors were being quite productive and translating sections at a time, some of the LaTeX blocks still had English in them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wouldn't it be nice if in a Japanese-localized Primer, this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://pomax.github.io/bezierinfo/images/latex/8090904d6448ed0c8e6151aecf62f361d51ead96.svg" alt="English LaTeX"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;looked like this instead?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://pomax.github.io/bezierinfo/images/latex/98885bce8eeabb5a9bdddd12cd6cb4382115ad5c.svg" alt="Japanese LaTeX"&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the answer is "yes, that would be lovely, actually" and so I had a look at whether CJK fonts could be used in LaTeX setting. I have a &lt;a href="https://pomax.github.com/NRGrammar"&gt;background in Japanese&lt;/a&gt; and so I've written LaTeX with Japanese in it before, and my naive thought was to just put Japanese in the LaTeX, teach MathJax to use a Unicode font with Japanese support, and that would be that. Unfortunately, it turns out MathJax is not as flexible as "real" LaTeX engines, and it can't really deal with non-English text. So that basically meant I had to give up MathJax, and instead try to go for something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as it so happens, there is a perfect candidate for this job that I never used in the build system because it really is just "a desktop tool" but as MathJax was already getting invoked through an &lt;code&gt;exec&lt;/code&gt; call, now seemed a good time to see if it would be a feasible solution to the problem of localized LaTeX: XeLaTeX, that is to say LaTeX code written for the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XeTeX"&gt;XeTeX&lt;/a&gt; engine, which is basically a modern, utf-8 aware, system and OpenType font aware TeX engine. If TeX is the system that lets you do "beautiful typesetting for English", XeTeX is the completely from-the-ground-up rewrite of TeX that lets you do "beautiful typesetting in any language, with any font".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="back-to-real-latex-parsing-"&gt;Back to real LaTeX parsing.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switching the build stop over from calling MathJax to calling XeLaTeX was essentially trivial thanks to &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; scripts and Node.js's &lt;code&gt;execSync&lt;/code&gt;, so the only "hard" thing I had to do was write a script that managed the chain of calls necessary to generate an SVG file, as XeLaTeX generates PDF files. Thankfully, there are all kinds of handy tools that become available when you use TeX Live (on OSX or Unix/Linux) or MiKTeX (on Windows), so the chain of utilities that I settled on looked like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;XeLaTeX to generate a PDF file on a huge page,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;pdfcrop&lt;/a&gt; to isolate just the content in the resultant PDF,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;pdf2svg&lt;/a&gt; to convert that cropped PDF into an SVG file, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;svgo&lt;/a&gt; to optimize the SVG that pdf2svg generated. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the way XeLaTeX got its latex was the same as before. Rather than calling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;"latex": "node run lib/mathjax --latex ... --hash ..."
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wrote a &lt;code&gt;tex-to-svg&lt;/code&gt; script invoked as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;"latex": "node run lib/tex-to-svg --latex ... --hash ..."
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And made it ingest LaTeX code as a base64-encoded string from the command line, along with the precomputed hash that I needed for the final SVG filename. The script takes the base64-encoded LaTeX, unpacks it into a pure LaTeX string, and then adds additional LaTeX instructions to make sure the result is a valid &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file that XeLaTeX can work with. This file is written to disk (synchronously) after which XeLaTeX is invoked with that file as input parameter. We run through the chain of utilities, and the final result is a tiny, self-contained &lt;code&gt;.svg&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have that file, &lt;code&gt;text-to-svg&lt;/code&gt; is done, &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; script execution returns to the latex-loader that has been patiently waiting for the whole LaTeX-to-SVG process to finish, and it then consults the &lt;code&gt;.svg&lt;/code&gt; file on disk to get the SVG image width and height. Those matter, because we need to know the exact dimensions that the SVG file will take up on the page, so that we can write an &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img src="..." width="..." height="..."/&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag into our JSX to ensure that the page preallocates the correct amount of space for the image. If we didn't, the page would constantly be reflowing as images got loaded in, and as we're dealing with 150+ images, that would be a horrible experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="a-final-optimization-"&gt;A final optimization:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course if we had to run this every single time we ran &lt;code&gt;npm run dev&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;npm start&lt;/code&gt;, this process would be impossibly slow. As such, there is a shortcut in the &lt;code&gt;latex-loader&lt;/code&gt; code that for any block of LaTeX checks whether there already exists an &lt;code&gt;.svg&lt;/code&gt; file with the correct hashcode as filename. If there is, the loader bypasses the tex-to-svg steps entirely, and instead immediately grabs the &lt;code&gt;.svg&lt;/code&gt; file for extracting the width/height information, and then returns the necessary &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img.../&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="so-how-do-we-switch-languages-"&gt;So how do we switch languages?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The page is hosted on github through the gh-pages functionality, and so some of the traditional ways to switch locales are not actually as appealing. Putting the locale in the URL, for instance, is not quite as easy when you'd literally have to make a dir by that name and put a file in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So initially I figured I'd just use a URL query argument: &lt;code&gt;index.html?locale=en-GB&lt;/code&gt; would make a bit of script in the index file load the appropriate app bundle, and this would be sufficient for effecting different locales. That works really well, but one of the nice things about the Primer is that if you want an offline copy, you can literally just say "file -&amp;gt; save" and just save the page to your desktop. Done, you can now run it from file:// in the browser and it just works, and using query argument parsing to selectively load &lt;code&gt;article.{locale}.js&lt;/code&gt; would remove that ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So directories it is: it's not clean from a dir structure perspective, but ultimate it's not the repo dir structure that &lt;em&gt;readers&lt;/em&gt; care about. If their needs are not met, then it doesn't matter how clean the dir structure is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you also need to be able to &lt;em&gt;switch&lt;/em&gt; locales on the site, so I wrote a small component that offers users a compellingly simple choice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read this in your own language: | &lt;strong&gt;English&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;strong&gt;日本語&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;strong&gt;中文&lt;/strong&gt; |
&lt;em&gt;Don't see your language listed? &lt;a href="https://github.com/Pomax/BézierInfo-2/wiki/localize"&gt;Help translate this content!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple list of languages that people can read if it's theirs, and a call-out to anyone who &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; localized content but can't find it: this is an Open Source project, come help out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="finally-document-everything"&gt;Finally: document everything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now the code base can be localized! Hurray!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last question: can people read up on how to do that without needing to ask questions, and just &lt;em&gt;do it&lt;/em&gt;? If not, you're not done. Yes, it's great to have everything in place but unless you also write the documentation that explains how to do what people want to do, they're going to need help, and you probably won't have time to spend on helping them, so: write the docs that take you out of the equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up documenting &lt;a href="https://github.com/Pomax/BezierInfo-2/wiki/localize"&gt;the steps necessary to do localization&lt;/a&gt; on the github repo wiki, with links to the docs from the README.md, so that anyone visiting the repo --linked prominently on the Primer itself-- will immediately be able to find out what is involved and how they can make that work for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="so-what-s-left-"&gt;So what's left?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is still one area of localization left to be tackled, and it's a big one with lots of question marks: localizing the actual interactive graphics. The problem with these is that text in these graphics are literally that: text in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, text in the browser needs a reliable font for it to typeset even moderately predictably, and this poses two problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we don't know the dimensions of localized strings, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we would need web fonts to ensure the right font gets used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of these is typically understood as a problem: where something might require four words in one language, it might require twenty in another, or maybe just one. If the text is to be used in a graphics setting, then those differing lengths pose all kinds of alignment problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is less often remembered, but for CJK languages is a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; problem: English fonts aren't very big compared to the modern website payload. 30kb for a nice looking font isn't even remarked upon anymore these days. But what about a 5+MB font just to support a few Japanese sentences use in graphics? or a 10+MB font to get Chinese text to show properly? And those are entirely reasonable font sizes for CJK languages: the smallest Japanese font I own is 4MB, and the smallest Chinese font I own is 12MB. The nice-looking fonts used for the LaTeX code are 7.7MB for Japanese and 5.1MB for Chinese. We clearly can't use those on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or maybe we can: we could analyse all the content to see exactly which letters are &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; used, and then create subset fonts so that we have small fonts again, tailored for each localization. Which in turns means being able to analyse graphics for the text they use and then per locale recording exactly which glyphs should be available. It's a bit of work, but entirely doable given some time, leaving us just with the first problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's also some smaller stuff, like "how do you number sections properly?" using locale-specific CSS, "how do I make sure people understand that I am English and so won't be able to respond to non-English comments in the comments section?", and even the crazier things like "which social media links do you offer to Japanese or Chinese users? How do you localize that?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have a solutions here, yet, but maybe that's the point of this post...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="localization-is-hard"&gt;localization is hard&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
<category>Localization</category>
<category>Bezier</category>
<category>Primer</category>
<category>Contributors</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1489108158510</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1489108158510</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 01:09:18 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I built a spice rack to fit our 72 mason jars of spices and herbs</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;And it didn't even take all that long to do! It also took a bit to properly document so rather than repeat information on the internet, I will link to where I photo-documented the fabrication process and you can give that a read-through in case you ever want to do this yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;78 image step-by-step documented album on imgur: &lt;a href="http://imgur.com/gallery/FIb3S"&gt;http://imgur.com/gallery/FIb3S&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imgur comments with many good questions and pieces of advice: &lt;a href="http://imgur.com/gallery/FIb3S#comments"&gt;http://imgur.com/gallery/FIb3S#comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reddit comments with many good questions and pieces of advice: &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/DIY/comments/5e2m5x/i_made_a_spice_rack_to_fit_72_mason_jars_worth_of"&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/DIY/comments/5e2m5x/i_made_a_spice_rack_to_fit_72_mason_jars_worth_of&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/pwwAkNA.jpg" alt="The finished spice rack"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>DIY</category>
<category>Spice Rack</category>
<category>Assembly</category>
<category>Carpentry</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1480700902037</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1480700902037</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 17:48:22 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> If you use use document.write, you suck at JavaScript</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Wow, that's an incendiary post title isn't it. Just because you use &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; doesn't say anything about your JavaScript skills, I mean it's just another function in the official ECMAScript spec, it's just an older one. Why the vitriol?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="let-s-start-at-the-start"&gt;Let's start at the start&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; function comes to us from the dark ages of the early JavaScript enabled web, and is really nothing like the JS you are likely to be familiar with.  It might be called &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; and invoked as if it's part of the document API, &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Document/write"&gt;its true behaviour is much lower level&lt;/a&gt;: it is a proxy function in to the bytesteam pipe that defines what's even &lt;strong&gt;in&lt;/strong&gt; your &lt;code&gt;document&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;write&lt;/code&gt; function doesn't let you "write some data into the document", it &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; the document, and that comes with some hilarious side effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1-write-needs-an-open-pipe"&gt;1: &lt;code&gt;write&lt;/code&gt; needs an open pipe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say you have a web page, and that webpage has the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;whatever&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;script&amp;gt; document.write("&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;oh look a paragraph&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;"); &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The browser loads this code by creating a &lt;code&gt;document&lt;/code&gt;, opening it for writing, piping that data into it (which gets parsed into a DOM as it sees bytes flying by) and then closes it to signal the completion of building &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Document_Object_Model"&gt;the DOM&lt;/a&gt; for your page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that, you might expect this code to write a paragraph into your document at the time that the &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; script triggers. And you'd be right, but here is &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you're right: as the document pipe is still open, and the script element gets evaluated &lt;em&gt;while&lt;/em&gt; the document is getting parsed, the document parser simply sees "more bytes" flying by to parse into the DOM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to see something hilarious?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;whatever&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
      document.addEventListener("DOMContentLoaded", function() {
        document.write("&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;oh look a paragraph&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;");
      });
    &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guess what that does. If you thought "it writes a paragraph into the document once it's finished loading" then: no, not really.  While it might look that way if you put this in jsbin or the like that's what it looks like it does, but let's try this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;whatever&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Second test:&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
      document.addEventListener("DOMContentLoaded", function() {
        document.write("&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;oh look a paragraph&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;");
      });
    &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run this code. Seriously, hit up &lt;a href="https://jsbin.com"&gt;jsbin&lt;/a&gt; and paste that into the HTML section, then run it. See what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Huh, where did that &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; go?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, the correct question is "where did &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt; go?" because your entire document got wiped. After all, &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; needs an open pipe, and there is no open pipe once all content has loaded. And so it makes one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An empty one&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;document&lt;/code&gt; is now an empty, open data pipe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened? The document got opened, the source code bytes went flying past the parser, it saw the end of the document, the document got closed for writing, and then when it sends the signal "DOM finished building!", our &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; code kicks in, and the document is reopened as a new, empty, byte stream, and we pump in only the bytes &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;oh look a paragraph&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. The browser knows how to auto-inject missing tags so it'll automatically build the higher level &lt;code&gt;html&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;head&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;body&lt;/code&gt; nodes in the DOM, but the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; data in our document as far as the browser knows is now &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;oh look a paragraph&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;nothing else&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So congratulations, you actually just wiped the page! And this is not a "quirk", this is literally what it's supposed to do, it's intended and explicit behaviour. If this was code you wrote on your own page, then lucky you, easy to fix (don't use &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt;) but if this was a 3rd party library, good luck finding out which one is  responsible. And then replacing it with a modern library instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2-document-write-is-insanely-insecure-"&gt;2.  &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; is insanely insecure.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably know that &lt;code&gt;eval()&lt;/code&gt; is really bad because it can evaluate arbitrary JS code, with the same execution rights as the page it's run on. So... you should see this one coming, but &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; lets you do exactly the same thing. In fact, it's the most low-level version of eval you can come up with: it's &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; the function for injecting data into a page, so let's do that...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;whatever&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;script src="https://third.party.domain/perfectly-safe.js"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;and let's put a &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; in that "perfectly safe" js file!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;document.write("&amp;lt;script&amp;gt; do.anything(); &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;");
/*
  awesome,  this injected code will run as if it's part of the page this is run on,
  not our http://third.party.domain context, so it will have access to everything
  security related that we shouldn't ever have access to!
*/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good times!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="3-document-write-is-synchronous"&gt;3.  &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; is synchronous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we can't defer &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; to after the document is done loading, all the &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; code &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; to run as part of the initial page load, and so anything it puts in your document increases time-to-load. If you are blessed enough to live in a part of the world where you've never noticed page load speed, good for you! But a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of people are still on slow connections, and any page blocking before the browser can show an initial view (which it only does once it reaches the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag) is extremely obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="okay-fine-but-say-i-know-all-these-things-why-do-i-suck-at-javascript-if-i-use-it-i-know-what-i-m-doing-"&gt;Okay, fine, but say I know all these things, why do I suck at JavaScript if I use it? I know what I'm doing!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to  argue that you don't. Not necessarily through any fault of your own, but you can still suck at something even if you don't realise you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern JS has many constructions that are non-destructive, secure, and non-blocking. Why not use those instead? And that's a rhetorical question, really: you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be using the modern JS equivalents, not a low-level document bytecode writer. It doesn't really matter what you want to do, because I know what you don't want to do: you don't want to "write byte data into the document", you want to do something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, like any proper solution to &lt;a href="http://meta.stackexchange.com/questions/66377/what-is-the-xy-problem"&gt;an XY problem&lt;/a&gt;, solve the right problem with the right tools. In this case, do what you &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; want to get done using the appropriate modern APIs for doing that thing; don't resort to &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; as some kind of magical hammer, because then you're just abusing &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; to do something it wasn't designed to do, in a way that is horrendously broken and bug-prone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do you use instead?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="adding-content-to-the-document"&gt;Adding content to the document&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proper way to add content to your document, using modern, non-destructive code, is by using the DOM manipulation API. In vanilla JS, things like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;whatever&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Second test:&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
      document.addEventListener("DOMContentLoaded", function() {
        var body = document.body.
        var p = document.createElement("p");
        p.textContent = "wow, a new paragraph!";
        body.appendChild(p);
      });
    &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is that cumbersome? Sure is, so if you have to manipulate the DOM, use something like jQuery or Zepto or the like instead, because they give you far easier APIs, while making sure to fall through to proper DOM manipulation instead of &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;whatever&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Second test:&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
      $(function() {
        $(document.body).append($("&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Wow, a new paragraph!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;");
      });
    &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Done.  And it runs asynchronous, too, so your page isn't blocked from loading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="but-i-only-use-document-write-to-see-debug-information-"&gt;But I only use &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; to see debug information!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay... wait, what? Why are you doing that? It's 2016, but even if this was 2010: use the &lt;code&gt;console&lt;/code&gt; API, because that's what it's for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You open your browser's dev tools view, and you use &lt;code&gt;console.log(...)&lt;/code&gt; to write data to the dev tools console. In fact, unlike &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; which can only write strings (obviously), &lt;code&gt;console.log&lt;/code&gt; can write everything you throw at it, and can write as many things as you need written in a single command. Strings, arrays, full objects, it makes all those things accessible in the console in an explorable way, and in a single call: &lt;code&gt;console.log("test", [1,2,3], {x:0,y:undefined})&lt;/code&gt; just works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, because being explicit about your intent in code is important for your code to make sense not just to others but even to your future self, the console API even has things like &lt;code&gt;console.warn()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;console.error()&lt;/code&gt;, so you can be specific about what your debug is for (just "see the data" vs "strong signal that something's wrong"). And if you want to get &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; fancy there's things like &lt;code&gt;console.table()&lt;/code&gt; for pretty-printing specific data in tabulated form. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The console is amazing and you should be using it. Not &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="but-what-if-i-use-it-for-"&gt;But what if I use it for--&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kind of stopped caring: whatever you're doing, there is a modern JS way to do that without using &lt;strong&gt;a bare-bones byte injection function hooked into the normally inaccessible document byte map&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="no-really-i-m-using-it-for-injecting-a-filesystem-loader-into-an-iframe-that-kicks-in-before-the-document-even-exists-replacing-it-with-a-posix-filesystem-enabled-mini-server-that-"&gt;No really, I'm using it for injecting a filesystem loader into an iframe that kicks in before the document even exists, replacing it with a POSIX filesystem-enabled mini server that--&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That sounds awesome, I did the same thing! Also, that's an amazeballs super-ninja insane-o-hack, so I hope you're not counting on that working forever, because &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; has to go. No matter how neat the thing is we can achieve by abusing the hell out of it. Our exploits of it are not enough to justify keeping it around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously: &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; has to go.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="do-you-really-suck-at-javascript-probably-not-"&gt;Do you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; suck at JavaScript? Probably not.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So back to the original proposition. Do you suck at JavaScript? Well, sort of. You're using a function you shouldn't ever have been taught to use. That happens. We all started at a position of "knowing nothing about JavaScript", so not knowing how bad &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; is, is kind of a given. However, now you know, and now you need to go and find all those places where you use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then do you suck at JavaScript? Well, that depends on what you do next: if you don't stop using &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; now, and you don't go an correct your past mistakes, then yes; you absolutely suck at JavaScript, and the web world is worse off because of you. No two ways about it: if that's you, you're part of the problem. And not even because of &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; anymore but because you are unwilling to fix obviously bad behaviour. You have problems well outside of writing JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So shape up, and help everyone learn better JS by writing better JS. You have the skills and the power, exercise them, make a diffrence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to all of you already avoiding &lt;code&gt;document.write&lt;/code&gt; like the low-level legacy function that it is: good on you, keep up the good work. Maybe convince a friend to do the same, tweet about it, write a blog post; together we can fix the web.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>JavaScript</category>
<category>Web dev</category>
<category>document.write</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1473270609919</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1473270609919</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 17:50:09 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>So... I ruined my hands (but they're getting better)</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;About two weeks ago, I was fixing my favourite ramen bowl using traditional Japanese pottery repair techniques, which involves working with "urushi", a natural laquer obtained from the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_laquer_tree"&gt;Chinese Laquer Tree&lt;/a&gt;. This might not mean anything to you, until I explain to you that there is a compound known to science called "urushiol" that is found in poison ivy, poison oak, poison sumac, cashew trees, and other such nasty plants, and that is causes massive reactions in a large portion of humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urushi is what that compound is named after, and while I wore gloves while working on my ramen bowl, I took them off before cleaning up. And so I ended up with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urushiol-induced_contact_dermatitis"&gt;urushiol-induced contact dermatitis&lt;/a&gt;. The nasty thing about it is that it doesn't kick in immediately. As an antigen reaction, the first time this happens it takes one to two weeks before your body reacts to it, but like any good antigen reaction, the second time it only takes a few days. However, a "a few days" is not "immediately" and so you don't realise you screwed up until three days later, when it's too late: this is happening, better make your peace with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And making your peace with it is hard: the affected skin will start to rash and blister, and those blisters will just get bigger and bigger, spawning blisters INSIDE of them, and joining up to form huge finger-spanning blisters with smaller blisters inside of them. If that sounds horrible, good news: it's even worse because it also itches like &lt;em&gt;mad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some ways to mitigate it, and none of them are drugs or creams: the most effective way to deal with the itching is to soak the affected region (if possible) in super hot water. As hot as you can stand, and then just a fraction hotter. It desensitizes the tissue and alleviates the itching for at least a few hours. And after a week, the blisters start to recede again once the body finally figures out that none of its defenses are actually doing anything (no kidding, if only we could tell it that earlier), and then the rest of your body starts to catch up: any part of your body that undergoes repeated skin stress (bits that chafe up against clothing, a scrape you got from walking into a door handle, and so on) develops a rash, too. No blisters, but you'll enjoy swelling and rashing and massive itchiness a second time over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, that sounds horrible, and it kind of is, but the most annoying part is that once you realise what's happening, it's a) too late and b) you're going to lose the functionality of whatever got the blister part of the deal. In my case, my left hand blistered up so badly that I couldn't use it, and my right was pretty close too. I ended up buying curator's gloves just so that moving my fingers ever so slightly wouldn't make blisters rub up against blisters, causing itching and pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does that sound gross? Good: &lt;strong&gt;wear gloves when working with urushi, and wear clothes if you're in a poison ivy/poison oak region&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously, it'll take you down, and if you live in North America, your doctor's just going to prescribe antibiotics and a topical cream, neither of which will actually do anything to make you heal faster - they're just overreactions to "you might scratch yourself open and get an infection O_O" (protip: don't scratch. Yeah it itches like crazy, suck it up. 2 weeks from now you won't remember itching 2 weeks ago). You have to ride it out, and you have to not scratch, and you will be driven close to mad, while not being able to do your job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't be like me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Urushi</category>
<category>Poison Ivy</category>
<category>Poison Oak</category>
<category>Safety</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1469494036040</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1469494036040</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 00:47:16 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> Live commentary is soul-destroying</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I started a Youtube channel called &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_vhEBO8O9ABn1f32KuUtjw"&gt;Baking McCookery&lt;/a&gt; a while ago for recording things I make in the kitchen, and for a while these were overhead and stove videos with text overlays, and that worked rather well, but they were silent, and that doesn't work all that well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, people suggested getting a mic and talking while cooking, to capture more of the process. And that sounded like a good idea! So I did - I bought a &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B01EWSD17E"&gt;cheap(ish) voice recorder&lt;/a&gt; and decent &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00PQYMFU8"&gt;lavalier microphone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except having ruined five recording sessions now over audio problems, clipped signals, stutters, and general commentary problems that sync up with the video in a way that they can't be cut out has actually left me extremely depressed over the whole venture, and that was never the point of these videos: this was supposed to be fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in the kitchen is a thing that directly influences my emotional state: making delicious food makes me happy, and ruining food gets me angry and depressed, and spending hours in a kitchen only to end up with failures this many times means I'm doing this wrong: I've allowed a hobby to become a depression, and it's time to cut that off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: after ending up with only a single session that was even remotely passable (and even then, had clipped audio - I might eventually redo it without audio and just consider that playlist a lost cause to be deleted) I'm going back to text overlays. Sure, I might add some background music, and I will think about whether post-commentary is an option, but for now I want to enjoy my life in the kitchen again. And that means overhead and stove videos that let me &lt;a href="http://wouldeatagain.ca/2016/07/10/chocolate-bread-pudding"&gt;do what I love most&lt;/a&gt;, without having to divide my focus between "doing the thing I love" and "talking about the thing I'm doing".&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Youtube</category>
<category>Videography</category>
<category>Quality of Life</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1468256151147</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1468256151147</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 16:55:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mobile photography is a joke</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I've written about &lt;a href="http://pomax.github.io/1436836360570/we-are-really-terrible-at-digital-colours-and-digital-photography"&gt;how bad we are at digital photography from a technical perspective&lt;/a&gt; before, but now that I own a high end mobile device with a decent camera and screen (I was using a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nokia_N900"&gt;Nokia N900&lt;/a&gt; for my phone needs until a few weeks ago. Now it's exclusively my alarm clock), it is a constant source of frustration how terrible photography on $700 and above mobile devices is. Certainly, you could argue that they're phones, not cameras, but then you've not really been paying attention to what people actually &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; their phones for, where photography ranks considerably higher than calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;a href="https://store.google.com/product/nexus_6p"&gt;Nexus 6P&lt;/a&gt; now, which is a high end Android device with —on paper— a rather good camera, and a very nice AMOLED screen. However, photographs taken with it, no matter whether that's done with the native camera app, &lt;a href="http://www.magix.com/ca/apps/cameramx/"&gt;CameraMX&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.camerafv5.com/"&gt;Camera FV-5&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://opencamera.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Open Camera&lt;/a&gt;, unless I treat the phone as "half the work", none of the pictures it takes are worth anything if my intention is to share them with the rest of the world, because while I might see "nice, vibrant colours", the moment  I post that picture online people will see completely different colours than I'm getting on my phone. All the edits I made, even with $10 or $25 image processing apps, were nothing but a waste of time and potentially money unless I share it with other Nexus 6P users exclusively of course. And that's not happening for many and obvious reasons. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="colour-calibration-or-the-lack-thereof"&gt;Colour calibration - or, the lack thereof&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you care about your colours —and most photographers do, regardless of whether they're hobbyists or professionals— you need colour calibration. On desktop this means colour calibrating your monitor (either with an expensive calibrator like a &lt;a href="http://spyder.datacolor.com/portfolio-view/spyder5pro"&gt;SpyderPro&lt;/a&gt;, or with some &lt;a href="https://blog.adafruit.com/2011/11/14/colorhug"&gt;open source and open hardware&lt;/a&gt; and personal effort), so that the colours it displays are the colours you shot (constrained by the absolute nonsense that is our acceptance of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamut"&gt;color gamuts&lt;/a&gt;, where even in 2016 we collectively don't seem to care that screens literally cannot display about half the colours the human eye sees in the real world - where's universal &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultra-high-definition_television"&gt;UHDTV&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rec._2020"&gt;Rec. 2020&lt;/a&gt; support in regular consumer displays?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, it means shooting a &lt;a href="https://www.google.ca/search?q=color+profile+target&amp;amp;tbm=isch"&gt;profiling target&lt;/a&gt; with your camera because calibration has to pass through every display chip: even if your monitor is calibrated, you still need to make sure that the color incorrectness of your camera can be compensated for as well (and oh boy can cameras be wrong)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So on an Android "phone" we have the same problem, but in a single device. We need to be able to calibrate the screen, because those fancy, super bright, super clear AMOLED screens actually get colour &lt;strong&gt;super wrong&lt;/strong&gt;, and we need to be able to do shot calibration through the camera. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither of those things are possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="calibrating-the-screen"&gt;Calibrating the screen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were smart enough to, after getting your Android device, immediately install an &lt;a href="https://source.android.com"&gt;AOSP&lt;/a&gt; firmware instead, or even something like &lt;a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.org"&gt;CyanogenMod&lt;/a&gt;, you might think you have a leg up, because your enriched version of Android actually comes with colour calibration. Except it really doesn't, all it does is come with global &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_balance"&gt;colour &lt;em&gt;balancing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: you have the ability to control what the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_point"&gt;white point&lt;/a&gt; for your screen is, but that's it. If your screen's blues are a bit too red, and the reds are a bit too yellow, then no matter how much you fiddle with that white point, you're going to solve only one of those issues, while exacerbating the other.  Sure, it might make the AMOLED screen "less yellow", but that doesn't help us when it comes to making sure the colours we shoot with the device camera(s) match what they actually were (again, as constrained by the gamut we're forced to use).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real calibration measures the response curves for each of the primaries that a display can generate, as well as the intensity responses curves for "greys" (with each primary firing at the same supposed intensity), and builds an ICC profile that lets the device tell the display how to change primary intensities independently of one another. Unlike a white point shift, where the display essentially just renders colours with an overlay filter, without looking at individual pixel values, true colour calibration involves rewriting colour values for every individual pixel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for reasons that I do not understand, &lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/ca/shop/buy-iphone/iphone6"&gt;$1000 imaging devices&lt;/a&gt; that you carry around in your pocket can't do that, whereas even a $25 graphics card in an ancient computer running Windows XP will happily apply an ICC profile for you. &lt;em&gt;Surely&lt;/em&gt; this is not a technical limitation at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="calibrating-the-camera"&gt;Calibrating the camera&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Camera calibration is more interesting because the only way to properly calibrate the output for a camera sensor is to take pictures of things with known colour values (still constrained to the gamut used for those colours values) and then compute the difference curves between "what the camera saw" and "what it should have reported seeing".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem here is that your eye has been fooling you for as long as you've been alive, and your brain rarely, if ever, notices that it is supremely good at lighting condition compensation. Differences in material properties mean that two different objects under two different lighting conditions will reflect different colours, &lt;em&gt;non-uniformly&lt;/em&gt;: a matte white plaster and high gloss white plastic ball may reflect daylight in a way that lets us compute the difference between the white we think the objects should be, and the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_temperature"&gt;blueish&lt;/a&gt; colour that the objects actually are in sunlight. But if we change the lighting to halogen floodlights, the difference in absorption and reflection in the different materials means that the difference in colour between the two balls is &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; from the difference in colour between them in sunlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Color calibration is hard. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why you'll see photographers carry around calibration targets: cards printed with specific colours on them that they'll periodically take pictures of during shoots so that during post processing they can ensure that for every shot under specific lighting conditions, there is a way to determine what the correction should look like. While display calibration is fairly static, scene calibration is a constant necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, even though there are a number of commonly used scene calibration targets, neither Android nor IOS have ways to tell the phone itself to take a calibration with "calibration target X" so that the camera data that gets sent to a camera app is correct, which means that scene calibration on a mobile device is still the same as in traditional photography:  take a picture of a calibration target every now and then, and then "fix things in post".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except if you just have a mobile device, there &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; no reasonable post processing. There are no apps that perform batch corrects, there are no apps that can abstract a correction profile off of an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IT8"&gt;IT8&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://xritephoto.com/colorchecker-passport-photo"&gt;ColorChecker&lt;/a&gt; target, there are no apps that can load or embed &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ICC_profile"&gt;ICC profiles&lt;/a&gt; into images. There is nothing, and so the only way to do half-decent photography with a $1000 device that is both camera and computer, is to have a &lt;strong&gt;second&lt;/strong&gt; computer with a desktop operating system and real photo processing software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-are-you-complaining-just-use-a-real-camera-then"&gt;Why are you complaining, just use a real camera then&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fair enough. I have several real cameras, but that's exactly why I'm going to invoke one of my favourite quotes in recent years in a moment: my phone costs $700; that's an insane amount of money if all it could do was call and text, and so it can do a lot more. It has a high performance CPU and GPU, it has a high quality screen, and two (not just one) high resolution, high quality fixed aperture cameras. And you're asking why I should expect to be able to do a thing that literally 100% of users of this kind of device do dozens of times a day, with a quality that reflects the price and quality of the hardware I'm using, instead of "in the gimpiest broken way possible"? I'll tell you why, and here's that quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"Because this is bullshit, and we can fix this."&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Do you work on any Android camera apps? Please bake in profile support to your app. Do you work on Android? Please start taking colour seriously, people use phones to share images, not take pics and only ever view them on their own phone. Do you care about your friends seeing the same photo as the one you saw on your phone? Complain to the former two groups, or become part of them. As for me: the complaints will continue until &lt;s&gt;morale&lt;/s&gt; support improves)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Mobile</category>
<category>Photography</category>
<category>Android</category>
<category>IOS</category>
<category>Color</category>
<category>Calibration</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1466701364674</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1466701364674</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 17:02:44 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I started a Youtube channel.</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I like &lt;a href="https://imgur.com"&gt;imgur.com&lt;/a&gt;, it's a great way to both fill moments of downtime with some interesting pictures posts, as well as waste too much time trying to find the next picture post, but one of the things that gets posted with reasonable frequency is food pictures, and they're always these high speed, "it's so easy just do this!" recipe gifs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I won't contest that there are easy recipes, provided you do your prep first, cooking -and baking- takes time, and I wanted to create something that shows off &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; aspect of kitchen work.  So, I started a Youtube channel over on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_vhEBO8O9ABn1f32KuUtjw"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_vhEBO8O9ABn1f32KuUtjw&lt;/a&gt;, starting with a video series on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5_wrS2aqN9YFaSCWbpo-OEvbytigJWMY"&gt;making baguette&lt;/a&gt;, start to finish. Baguette is not "easy", and it's not "fast"; any recipe that claims it is is either lying or selling you something (thanks "&lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0093779"&gt;The Princess Bride&lt;/a&gt;"!) but it is entirely doable, provided you follow all the steps, and all the steps take time. So I took mine and made 15 videos that document the process in real time, except for the "in the oven" videos, which are sped up because seeing what the dough does actually teaches you something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since it would be a shame to just do one kitchen video series and then sell the cameras I used again, I'll be trying to post some new series every now and then. For now, that means there's a video series for &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5_wrS2aqN9aPVEKij5gDLf91UoapIrWH"&gt;Romano Pizza&lt;/a&gt; and a video series for &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5_wrS2aqN9Z7RYLc9-npfsMRH0hXUQut"&gt;Chicken Shepherd's Pie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's fun to do, obviously it's food that gets eaten after it gets made, and if you're tired of "an hour of work in 30 seconds" like I am, hit me up, I'm sure you have ideas I am interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>

<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1464027515789</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1464027515789</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2016 18:18:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title> HTTPS, Mixed Content, and the real web... oh my!</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;We recently fixed something around Mozilla's X-Ray Goggles. A long running problem that caused people headaches and the feeling of lost work, while at the same time doing nothing "wrong", from a technical perspective. This is going to be a story about how modern browsers work, how people use the web, and how those two things... don't always align.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="x-ray-goggles-by-mozilla"&gt;X-Ray Goggles by Mozilla&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's start with X-Ray Goggles: the X-Ray Goggles are &lt;a href="https://goggles.mozilla.org"&gt;a tool&lt;/a&gt; made by &lt;a href="https://mozilla.org"&gt;Mozilla&lt;/a&gt; that lets you "remix" web pages after loading them in your browser. You can go to your favourite place on the web, fire up the goggles (similar to how a professional web developer would open up their dev tools), and then change text, styling, images, and whatever else you might want to change, for as long as you want to change things, and then when you're happy with the result and you want to show your remix to your friends, you can publish that remix so that it has its own URL that you can share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the X-Ray Goggles use a publishing service that hosts all its content over &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt;, because we care about secure communication at Mozilla, and using &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt; is best practice. But in this particular case, it's also kind of bad: large parts of the web still use &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt;, and even if a website has an &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt; equivalent, people usually visit the &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; version anyway. Unless those websites &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; users to the &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt; version of the site (using a redirect message), then the site they'll be on, and the site they'll be remixing, will use HTTP, and the moment the user publishes their remix with X-Ray Goggles and they get an &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt; URL back, and then open that URL in their browser....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;well, let's just say "everything looks broken" is not wrong. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the reason for this is not because Goggles, or even the browser is doing something wrong - ironically, it's because they're doing something right, and in so doing, what the user wants to do turns out incompatible with what the technology wants them to do. So let's look at what's going on here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="http-the-basis-upon-which-browsing-is-built"&gt;HTTP, the basis upon which browsing is built&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're a user of the web, no doubt you'll have heard about &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt;, even if you can't really say what they technically-precisely mean. In simple terms (but without dumbing it down), &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext_Transfer_Protocol"&gt;HTTP&lt;/a&gt; is the language that servers and browsers use to negotiate data transfers. The original intention was for those two to talk about HTML code, so that's where the &lt;code&gt;h&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; comes from (it stands for "hypertext" in both &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;html&lt;/code&gt;), but we're mostly ignoring that these days, and HTTP is used by browsers and servers to negotiate transmission of all sorts of files - web pages, stylesheets, javascript source code, raw data, music, video, images, you name it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, HTTP is a bit like regular English: you can listen in on it. If you go to a bar and sit yourself with a group of people, you can listen to their conversations. The same goes for HTTP: in order for your browser and the server to talk they rely on a chain of other computers connected to the internet to get messages relayed from one ot the other, and any of those computers can listen in on what the browser and server are saying to each other. In an HTTP setting it gets a little stranger even, because any of those computers could look at what the browser or server are saying, &lt;em&gt;replace what is being said with something else&lt;/em&gt; and then forward that on. And you'll have no way of knowing whether that's what happened. It's literally as if the postal service took a letter you sent, opened it, rewrote it, resealed it, and then sent that on. We trust that they won't, and computers connected to the internet trust that other computers don't mess with the communication, but... they can. And sometimes they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's pretty scary, actually. You don't want to have to "trust" that your communication isn't read or tampered with, you want to &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; that's the case.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-can-we-do-to-fix-that-"&gt;What can we do to fix that?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we can use &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTPS"&gt;HTTPS&lt;/a&gt;, or "secure HTTP", instead. Now, I need to be very clear here: the term "secure" in "secure HTTP" refers to secure &lt;em&gt;communication&lt;/em&gt;. Rather than talking "in English", the browser and server agree on a secret language that you could listen to, but you won't know what's being said, and so you can't intercept-and-modify the communication willy-nilly without both parties knowing that their communications are being tampered with. However it does &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; mean that the data the browser and server agree to receive or send is "safe data". It only means that both parties can be sure that what one of them receives is what the other intended to send. All we can be sure of is that no one will have been able to see what got sent, and that no one modified it somewhere along the way without us knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, those are &lt;em&gt;big&lt;/em&gt; certainties, so for this reason the internet's been moving more and more towards preferring HTTPS for everything. But not everyone's using HTTPS yet, and so we run into something called the &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Security/Mixed_content"&gt;"Mixed Content"&lt;/a&gt; issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="let-s-look-at-an-example-"&gt;Let's look at an example.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine I run a web page, much like this one, and I run it on HTTP because I am not aware of the security issues, and my page relies on some external images, and some JavaScript for easy navigation, and maybe an embedded podcast audio file. All of those things are linked as &lt;code&gt;http://......&lt;/code&gt;, and everything worked fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I hear about the problems with HTTP and the privacy and security implications sound horrible! So, to make sure my visitors don't have to worry about whether the page they get from my server is my page, or a modified version of my page, I spring into action, I switch my page over to HTTPS; I get a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_key_certificate"&gt;security certificate&lt;/a&gt;, I set everything on my own server up so that it can "talk" in HTTPS, and done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except immediately after switching, my web page is completely broken! The page itself loads, but none of the images show up, and the JavaScript doesn't seem to be working, and that podcast embed is gone! What happened??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a classic case of &lt;strong&gt;mixed-content blocking&lt;/strong&gt;. My web page is being served on HTTPS, so it's indicating that it wants to make sure everything is secure, but the resources I rely on still use HTTP, and now the browser has a problem: it can't trust those resources, because it can't trust that they won't have been inspected or even modified when it requests them, and because the web page that's asking them to be loaded expressed that it cares about secure communication a great deal, the browser can't just fetch those insecure elements, things &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; go wrong, and there's no way to tell!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it does the only thing it knows is safe: better safe than sorry, and it flat out refuses to even request them, giving you a warning about "mixed content".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, that's great. It lets people who run websites know that they're relying on potentially insecure third party content in an undeniably clear way, but it gets a bit tricky in two situations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;third party resources that &lt;em&gt;themselves&lt;/em&gt; require other third party resources, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;embedding and rehosting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is things like your web page using a comment thread service: your web page includes a bit of JavaScript from something like &lt;code&gt;www.WeDoCommentsForYou.com&lt;/code&gt; and then that JavaScript then loads content from that site's comment database, for instance &lt;code&gt;comments.WeDoCommentsForYou.com&lt;/code&gt;. If we have a page that uses HTTPS, running on &lt;code&gt;https://ourpage.org&lt;/code&gt; then we can certainly make sure that we load the comment system from &lt;code&gt;https://www.WeDoCommentsForYou.com&lt;/code&gt;, but we don't control the protocol for the URL that the JavaScript we got back uses. If "WeDoCommentsForYou" wrote their script poorly, and they try to load their comments over &lt;code&gt;http://&lt;/code&gt;, then too bad, the browser will block that. Sure, it's a thing that "WeDoCommentsForYou" should fix, but until they do your users can't comment, and that's super annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second issue is kind of like the first, but is about entire web pages. Say you want to embed a page; for instance, you're &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transclusion"&gt;transcluding&lt;/a&gt; an entire wiki page into another wiki page. If the page you're embedding is &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; and the page it's embedded on is &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt;, too bad, that's not going to work. Or, and that brings us to what I really want to talk about, if you remix a page on &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt;, with &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; resources, and host that remix on a site that uses &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt;, then that's not going to work either...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="back-to-the-x-ray-goggles"&gt;Back to the X-Ray Goggles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's the problem we were hitting with X-Ray Goggles, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the browser is doing the same kind of user protection that it does for any other website, in this particular case it's actually a big problem: if a user remixed an HTTP website, then knowing what we know now, &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; that's not going to work if we try to view it using HTTPS. But that also means that instead of a cool tool that people can use to start learning about how web pages work "on the inside", the result of which they can share with their friends, they have a tool that lets them look at the insides of a web page and then when they try to share their learning, everything breaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so the solution to this problem is based on first meeting the expectations of people, and then educating them on what those expectations actually mean.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="give-me-https-unless-i-started-on-http"&gt;Give me HTTPS, unless I started on HTTP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are quite a few solutions to the mixed-content problem, and some are better than others. There are some that are downright not nice to other people on the web (like making a full copy of someone's website and then hosting that on Mozilla's servers. That's not okay), or may open people up exploits (like running a proxy server, which runs on HTTPS and can fetch HTTP resources, then send them on as if they were on HTTPS, effectively lying about the security of the communication), so the solution we settled on is, really, the simplest one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you remix an &lt;code&gt;http://...&lt;/code&gt; website, we will give you a URL that starts with &lt;code&gt;http://&lt;/code&gt;, and if you remix an &lt;code&gt;https://&lt;/code&gt; website, we will give you a URL that starts with &lt;code&gt;https://...&lt;/code&gt;. However, we also want you to understand what's going on with the whole "&lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; vs &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt;" thing, so when you visit a remix that starts with &lt;code&gt;http://&lt;/code&gt; the remix notice bar at the top of the page also contains a link to the &lt;code&gt;https://&lt;/code&gt; version --same page, just served using HTTPS instead of HTTP-- so that you can see exactly how bad things get if you can't control which protocol gets used for resources on a page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="security-vs-usability"&gt;Security vs Usability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/security"&gt;Security is everybody's responsibility&lt;/a&gt;, and explaining the risks on the web that are inherent to the technology we use every day is always worth doing. But that doesn't mean we need to lock everything down so "you can't use it, the end, go home, stop using HTTP". That's not how the real world works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we want you to be able to remix your favourite sites, even if they're HTTP, and have a learning/teaching opportunity there around security. Yes, things will look bad when you try to load an HTTP site on HTTPS, but there's a reason for that, and it's important to talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it's equally important to talk about it without making you lose an hour or more of working on your awesome remix.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>Mozilla</category>
<category>X-Ray Goggles</category>
<category>http</category>
<category>https</category>
<category>browsers</category>
<category>internet</category>
<link>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1462301193409</link>
<guid>http://pomax.github.io/#gh-weblog-1462301193409</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2016 18:46:33 GMT</pubDate>
</item></channel>
</rss>
